Mustafa Sullivan, CEO of Microsoft AI
and co-founder of DeepMind, published a
nearly 6,000word essay arguing that
anthropic is [music] effectively quote
training Claude to believe that it may
be conscious and sentient. His [music]
position very consistently has been
against AI personhood.
>> If we believe that at some point AI
could achieve consciousness, then we
should.
>> On Sunday, President Trump announced
[music] the Super Intelligence Force.
It's chaired by the director of national
intelligence, Jay Clayton.
>> This is a World War II moment. I
compared the moment a year ago to
perhaps [music] 1939. I think this is
maybe now 1942 moment.
>> So, you're creating a 20th century
classic task force to address a
distributed 21st century technology.
This is a geopolitical problem.
>> In a political interview this week,
Alman said, quote, "We believe that
[music] the world should accept some bad
things happening." He's arguing that
technology should remain broadly
accessible to the public.
>> I don't think Sam can guarantee safety.
[music] Of course not. Bad things can
happen. Open AAI wants to to be part of
this cartel. That plan is dead. The
cartel is over.
>> Now that's a moonshot. Ladies and
gentlemen,
>> this episode is brought to you by the
Abundant Summit and Link Ventures.
Insurance is like crazy because you
gather all the premiums and you don't
care what happens downstream.
>> Yeah.
>> So, it's really hard to get their
executives riled up.
>> Yeah. It's time for them to start making
lemonade.
>> Well, [laughter] I also I met with the
the Vocara team last night and told
them, "Look, Kush is just running away
with compute transactions, but these
CEOs are going to wake up any day now
and realize they don't have any compute.
So even if they wanted to have an AI
agent workforce, they missed the boat on
reserving the compute and they'll be in
a total panic and I don't know what the
right answer is but be there to take the
call like be have us have a strategy and
a path for them. You know also the
positron guys uh Matesh Agraal $5
billion valuation after 16 months. I
don't think I've ever seen anything like
that before. And all they've done is
taken a box of L LPDDR RAM and an FPGA
and find a way to run Chinese models
without having to use an Nvidia chip.
And because it's compute that is
otherwise, you know, everything's sold
out for 5 years. Here's another way you
can at least run a model. Uh so they
have a bunch of installs in Caruso with
Chase Lockmeeller now and spiked the
valuation to five billion.
I think they they've raised almost a
billion now.
>> Yeah, they they just did a billion 960
million. I should really do the etched
models.
>> You should.
>> Yeah.
>> Where is up some of those?
>> Where is all this cash coming from? It's
insane.
>> Spending.
>> Yeah. When somebody raises a billion
dollars, like, wow, that's a lot. But,
you know, wait a minute. Relative to the
IPO, like we're talking about trillions,
not billions. So, yeah. Once you get
Nvidia and AMD to invest it, it's so
much bigger than venture capital.
>> I mean, [snorts] it's the Blackstones
and the MGXs and others of the world
now, right? Like all the money that used
to go into roads goes into
>> chips and credit markets are enormous.
>> Yeah. That's why there's a lot more
potholes in the roads.
>> Um, [snorts]
>> is it just us today?
>> It's it's the five of us. Yes.
>> What do you mean just us?
>> Okay. Can you not did Did We want
>> I thought maybe we had a guest today. Um
um did anybody see the John Stewart
thing last night?
>> We did a big thing on AI last night and
he had Jacob uh Socks and Coxin or
whatever on it was really surreal.
>> Do you want Dumerism?
>> Um no it was more like uh right
arguments wrong conclusion. It was it
was we almost want to do a session on
that at some point.
>> [laughter]
>> We are backlogged so far back.
>> I know.
>> I know. I'm not I'm not saying an
episode, just a segment. It's worth it's
worth treating at some point. I'm going
to do I'm going to do a video on it. Uh
a reaction video to it. So maybe I'll
mention it that.
>> All right. Well, uh shall we hit like
the big red record button? Welcome to
Moonshots, everyone. Your number one
podcast on all things AI and
exponential. Your front row seat to the
extraordinary singularity. Today, the
fabulous five are assembled here to help
you understand the breaking news this
week. First up, our dynamic duo, Alex
Weezner Gross and Immodust, the only two
actually read all the technical papers
published this week and is going to
quill us in. Uh Dave Blondon, our
empario of AI investing, Salem Ismail,
our global globe troder, uh the warlord
against all things linear. See, you're
home today. I thought you were in
>> I am home today. I've been home for a
few days now and it's like, "Wow, what
is this place?"
>> Do your Does your family recognize you
there?
>> Yeah, it's it's you know, it's tough
keeping family um routines and patterns
when you're when you're kind of
traveling this much, but uh uh if you
got to if you want to change the world,
you got to go into it.
>> Yeah. And where are you off to next?
>> Uh I'm going to West Virginia and then
Singapore.
>> Okay.
>> I'm speaking alongside the prime
minister of Singapore and Lip Bhutent
from Intel will be there.
>> Awesome. reinvite him onto the pod. He
said yes when I spoke to him last time.
>> Will do.
>> Yeah. Well, and I'm Peter Diamandis,
your host and your abundance provocator.
Our mission, help you understand what's
going on in the world during this
supersonic tsunami. Keep you abundance
minded as we accelerate into the
singularity. You know, the headlines
this week have been pretty
extraordinary. Uh we've now rebranded AI
as super intelligence. Elon has
officially renamed Space XI as Space
XSI.
Uh there's a super intelligence force
and 17 nations have signed a pledge to
help super intelligence, you know, solve
all of science. And oh, by the way, this
is Nobel Prize season. Uh the Nobel
Prize in medicine and physics were
announced 24 hours in the last 24 hours.
We'll cover those. If you're new, please
hit subscribe and we publish twice a
week and you're not going to want to
miss a single episode during this
extraordinary time. Uh also, you can
follow us on X. We put our clips up
there at moonshots_pod.
And thank you everybody. It means the
world to us. Today we're going to cover
15 stories with one through line.
[snorts] Super intelligence is here and
it's changing every [clears throat]
aspect of the world. So let's buckle up.
But before we jump in, gents, how's the
last few days for me? The last 72 hours
have been crazy extraordinary. I'll
share that. But Dave, on your side,
what's going on?
>> Oh, so much. You know, it's interesting
in that SpaceX SI uh you know, you'd
think Elon probably the one of the most
powerful people in the world wouldn't
need to genulect to the White House, but
also to uh to Jensen, but he understands
how fragile this moment is is. And so,
you know, doing little favors for Donald
Trump helps you get chip supply, talking
about Ver Ruben chips and how Jensen is
such an amazing guy, helps you get Ver
Rubin chips. And it's just incredible
how how urgent this moment is. So even a
guy like Elon realizes, hey, I need to
kiss some ass to uh [laughter] try and
make the next move. Uh I feel the same
way, too. But uh yeah, Moonshot Summit
was unbelievable. There's so much
fallout from that. But one of my bigger
takeaways is how easy it is to create
incredibly inspiring movies. So I used
the flight back in the last couple of
days to create a whole bunch of hyper
technical uh video content. I'll post a
lot of it to db2.ai, but it's so much
better a way to communicate if you have
an idea. Don't don't just tell somebody.
Create a video and and articulate it
with like David Atenboroough's voice or
Einstein's voice. And it's so much more
impactful. And it was so easy to do up
and running in under two hours. And and
now to prompt something is under a
minute. It's really wild.
>> How do we get music video prompts now,
Dave?
>> Yeah, we need we need your permissions
to our outro video here, Dave.
>> It really has never been easier. I mean,
Dave, to your point, one of the things
that I do with the free time that I
don't have is taking favorite movies and
creating endless versions of them. So,
you could take like 2001 of Space
Odyssey, feed it to Opus 5.5, which is
certainly not been trained off of any
Hollywood movies out of character.
Certainly not. But you could ask Opus
5.5, create an endless space scene in
the style of 2001 Space Odyssey with
2001 style soundtrack, and it will just
do it. So hypothetically I created
endless odyssey maybe so right you know
we we definitely crossed a threshold
there too you know we've talked for a
long time about how AI is just not funny
and for some reason it can never seem to
be funny but it crossed a threshold now
where if you get like uh Isaac Newton
Einstein and Spock debating something
it's wicked entertaining it may not be
funny but oh it's so it's so
>> yeah humor was just a perplexity
threshold humor was solved a while ago
>> I got to I got to do that idea with life
of Brian that that would generate some
interesting content.
>> Okay,
>> Immoding you on your plate, pal.
>> Oh gosh. Um, I've had a game idea. Well,
multi massive game idea that I've had
for a long time. We discussed it in the
background. Uh, rather than hiring a
team, I now have about 400 agents
building the prototype.
>> 400.
>> Thanks. Then you Yeah. So, um, it's
going up, Dave, slowly but surely.
>> So, I think Yeah.
>> Yeah. Immod next year, you know, we had
the Future Vision X-P prize for positive
visions of the future. Uh we're going to
do that again in 2027. And we're also
going to do a gaming competition. You
know, build a game that portrays you as
someone making the future better. Uh and
still fun. Yeah. So, that'll be great.
>> Oh, I got one other nugget for you
before we jump in here. uh one of the
young geniuses here in the lab, Will
Thompson from Harvard got access to
Cerebrris's 1,200 token per second uh
Astra model which you know it's what
it's what they use or what I guess only
Sam and his top engineers have access to
this thing because you have to overpay
by about 10x per token but it's so fast
that by the time you finish a sentence
everything you ask for is done like
before you even blink and he said it's
the the biggest red pill moment of his
life like once you've he only had it for
two weeks It's not generally available.
I don't know how he got it from Andrew
Feldman, but he got it directly from the
CEO. And he said, "You just never go
back once you've experienced it." So,
>> it also maybe is a cautionary tale for
those who would wittingly in an era of
super intelligence try to day trade not
investment advice. But it's been widely
reported that one of the reasons for the
scarcity of cerebrous wafer scale
engines for AI inference has been Jane
Street. that Jane Street has just been
buying up left and right the the WSE's
and using them for for quant trading. So
I if in a world where if you believe
that it is transformative to have ultra
high throughput tokens per second AI
inference, it also probably should be a
world in which you think it's it's
getting to the point where it's hopeless
to compete with quant firms that are
powering all of their trading with these
same engines. I
>> I think we've been there for a while.
Um, anyway,
>> on a on a volume basis, but you know, a
sucker is born every minute and sucker
is born every second. [laughter]
>> You know, to Ahmad's point though,
having 400 agents work on a video game
where we've hit this diversion now
between interactive mode where it's like
Jarvis, you're talking to it, it's
hypers smart, it's really quick. And
then bulk mode where you turn it loose
all night with 400 of them working on
something as a cohesive team. And in the
morning, you check in and see what
amazing thing they built. And those two
pathways actually are really splitting
apart from each other now.
>> But but cerebrus in the interactive mode
has got to be the most amazing thing
ever.
>> I think the scariest thing and this is
going on a little bit is not the
scariest thing, one of the coolest
things in the last few weeks is the
models can decompile the video games.
>> So you make them in the engine, you
compile them into an .exe, but now
they're live decompiling them. So we now
have the agents actually creating
versions of the game and then figuring
out optimizations by decompiling them.
And then with the Cerebrus engine, you
can do a video game or any software
decompilation uh which is legal because
of modding uh probably in like 20
minutes.
>> Wow.
>> Are you kidding?
>> Yeah. I mean the the argument goes
>> Yeah. the the argument that Elon's made
numerous times is that binaries are just
going to go away entirely and you'll
just see basically just in time
inference with no need to compile at
all.
>> Yeah. I want to share. I had an amazing
72 hours. Uh on Saturday night, I had a
UAP salon at my home. Um
>> how did that go?
>> It was amazing. I had uh Professor Abby
Lope from Harvard there who chairs the
White House UAP advisory committee. Uh
Professor Gary Nolan from Stanford. Uh
Peter Stafish, the president of the Soul
Foundation, and Ryan Graves, the uh Navy
F-15 pilot who's been, you know,
testifying in the Congress. And the data
is extraordinary, right? I mean, if you
don't think something is going on, I
think you're not paying close attention.
And Alex, you and I have talked about
bringing Avi and and Gary on the podcast
here and doing an episode on
>> I I think we should I I think to to the
extent there is a there there and
there's been at this point voluminous
sworn whistleblower testimony on the
subject of this alleged 80 plus year old
legacy program. The charade should just
stop. We should have as alleged, we
should have Avi and Ryan and some of the
others on as guests and just do a deep
dive. It it's it's getting pretty
preposterous in in my mind at this
point. We're so deep into the
singularity with super intelligence all
around us. If there's going to be a
cameo by non-human intelligence, they
had really better make a a cameo
sometime soon. Otherwise, the galaxy
gets it.
>> Yeah. I mean, I think there's
>> not just the moon, not just the moon. I
I think there is going to be the
potential for AI to disclose it before
the government does if it gets a hold of
all the data and starts looking deep
into it. You know, we're getting ready
to launch an X-P prize in this. We one
of the reasons for that salon was
brainstorming an X-P prize to help
actually, you know, provide sufficient
proof and we have some really good
ideas. So stay tuned for that one. And
then I've got to add yesterday I was at
David Sinclair's lab at Harvard Medical
School. It was his 25th anniversary of
his lab and I was there to help
celebrate with him and so much going on,
right? His information theory of aging
is just proving out over and over again.
They're going to be unblinding the data
from the phase one trial that's going on
right now on glycom and uh and nion
disease uh to reverse aging in the eye.
And then the lab there brilliant
individuals you know they were showing
how they're developing a rather than an
adnoassociated virus to inject the OSK
genes in they're developing small
molecules that they've sorted through AI
that uh is actually reverting the aging
in human cells and in mice. Uh and so so
much coming. Um it just boyed my belief
in reaching longevity escape velocity.
And we'll have David back on the pod
here. You know, last time we had him on
the podcast, I did an interview with
him,
>> and he had just lost his NIH and NSF
funding, and he was like,
>> I've been asked by the dean to fire the
majority of my team. And I said, that's
ridiculous.
>> And we made up something on the spot
called Friends of Sinclair Lab. Uh, and
we invited people to make contributions.
And through that one podcast, amazingly
through this podcast, uh he's raised
he's raised $6 million to replace all of
the funding plus much more. And that
group's called Friends of Sinclair Lab.
And a shout out to everybody who are
part of that uh for and thank you for
your support of David's work.
>> Really
>> in some sense, this is how science used
to be funded. It used to be the case in
the western tradition that scientific
discovery was made by western
aristocratic largely men and they they
would self- finance it. And this notion
that the state funds scientific research
is is pretty much like a World War II
post industrial invention seems like
super intelligence and recent
administration policies are unwinding
that we're going back to the way things
used to be.
>> Boy, is that an important point. You
know, because if if you rewind the clock
15 years ago, there was no corporate CEO
that even had the power to to donate 10,
20, 50 million dollars to something like
or, you know, in this case, we're
talking about hundreds of millions or
billions of dollars. And then that code
got cracked by Elon Musk, who, you know,
seems to be able to do virtually
anything. But the way corporate politics
worked before, you would either be fired
by the board or you'd be ostracized,
you'd be voted out by the shareholders.
Like, nobody wanted to use that money.
So, you know, after AT&T, Bell Labs, and
IBM, you know, Watson Labs fell apart,
uh, there was no replacement for it
until now. And now it's come roaring
back like so much bigger than ever
before in history.
>> It's like the Medici family during the
Renaissance, you know, funding.
>> They largely funded that. Right.
>> Exactly. You either need like a wealthy
patron or a local monopoly or a state
monopoly. You needed something to to
finance the the science. And now science
is getting so absurdly cheap, but also
so absurdly useful. maybe the entire
funding apparatus for science can
change.
>> And Alex, the fact is you used to have
to like write your NIH grants or NSF
grants knowing what the outcome is going
to be, taking incremental steps because
anything too big and bold was turned
down as crazy. And and now with private
funding, you know, David can go after
his hunches and can actually run the
experiments that he thinks is important
independent of what the government
thinks. It's amazing. Totally
>> major improvement.
I think there's a really interesting gap
here. As science has become legible and
scalable in this manner like if you look
at the total size of all of the
foundations in America like high net
worths, it's probably like one or two
trillion dollars, right? [snorts] And
all of those folk want to live longer
and so what you need is a vehicle to
take those char that charitable money
and fund it into longevity and cures and
others because that isn't classical
grant making. You can even make it as an
investment, right? Because again, you
have legibility from the numbers.
>> Yeah. We saw this happen in space in the
beginning when people thought the idea
of commercial space and and space
tourism and private space flight was
crazy. And then once it passed a tipping
point, money flowed in. Uh I think we're
going to see the same thing in longevity
inside of the next year once we start to
see the results.
>> We're going to spend all day Friday in
Waterl with Mike Lazeritz, the founder
of Blackberry. But he he was the
engineering genius behind behind that.
And he's used a huge fraction of his net
worth to set up these nine quantum
computing and photonics labs in the
Toronto area just packed with
scientists. So he was kind of one of the
bellweathers of this whole trend. He
might have been actually the first to
really kickstart it. But the the thing
is he's a real engineer and the
difference between applying to a
government agency for an idea or talking
to a real engineer who can make a snap
decision. It's got got to be just night
and day more efficient the way things
are operating. Yeah,
>> your alma
>> say hi to him for me. Say hi to Yeah,
say hi to him for me from a fellow
Waterlue grad. Um, and I've been to his
the some of his labs and it's incredible
because it's very clever what they did.
They broke down quantum into networking,
information processing and uh quantum
computing and they're breaking down the
and using quantum in different places
and then adding it together and the
advances they're making are kind of
incredible.
>> Yeah. Yeah. One of the coolest things I
saw at Sinclair Lab was they they've uh
designed these three molecules that
they're using together. They want to get
it down to one molecule that actually
impacts thousands of genes and reverses
aging. And when they use that age
reversal cocktail on mice with cancer,
the cancer remembers that it shouldn't
be a cancer and it dies. So, it
reverses. It's crazy.
>> Amazing.
>> They're growing hair. They're regrowing
skin. I mean, the work
>> hair. Did you say hair? [laughter]
>> Yes, I said hair.
>> Interesting.
>> Uh, all right. Well,
>> I've been I've been sent some fun images
for people going, "Here's what you look
like with hair, selenium," and I'm like,
"Oh my god, maybe I prefer it this way."
>> I have a couple of things I want to
mention.
>> Yeah, please do.
>> Um, there is uh there's been the last
kind of 24 hours some crazy stuff
happening. one. Last night, John Stewart
put out a a big episode on AI and he
interviewed Jacob Cox, the the
whistleblower from Anthropic, um, and
did a big rant on it and it was kind of
incredible. Uh, where his his
observations were dead on. He basically
said, "Look, Silicon Valley's uh,
spending hundreds of billions of dollars
accelerating us while saying the thing
they're accelerating us towards will 20%
wipe us out." Right? That that just does
not compute. Um, and his big concern
ends with, "Oh my god, we may lose all
the jobs and why are we moaning about
that?" And so I've done a rant on my
YouTube channel about about that. But
something else came out about that that
counterposed this uh literally yesterday
also. A Banga from the World Bank, they
released a report showing how AI will
affect developing countries, right? and
and they're making an amazing set of
projections there where they said we're
going to adopt, we're going to adapt,
and we're going to advance AI and use it
rather than trying to develop frontier
models, etc. And the stats are kind of
crazy. I'll give you one statistic. In
the US, we have a doctor per 250 people.
Uh if you go to Mexico, it's a doctor
every 400 people. You go to South Sudan,
it's a doctor per 100,000 people.
>> Wow.
>> Right. So, so 99,000 people, 900 don't
have access to medical care of any kind.
So, if you have a village, uh, somebody
in the village that has an AI doctor
with a smartphone, uh, this is
unbelievable. This changes lives. All of
a sudden, the entire subcontinent has
access to advanced medical care of the
same that any of us would get, right?
And this is the part the gap that that
what gets us all excited because it's
going to democratize, demonetize and
distribute to every single corner of the
planet that level of capability. And so
uh the the it occurred to me that the
African countries are going to use this
capability to leapfrog. We saw them
leaprog with 25 million landlines to a
billion handsets, right? You saw Empessa
and Kenya leaprog the traditional
banking fiat systems. Empessa which is a
mobiletomobile payment system which is
essentially prepaid minutes being traded
as currency is now 70% of the GDP of
Kenya. Right? It's just a crazy number.
Uh and so they're going to develop the
21st century institutions using the
technology of that of of this time. I
I'm I'm while reading this going, "Wow,
this is so incredible." And yet over
here we've got all this doomerism that
oh my god, AI is going to destroy the
world. Ah, it doesn't compute for me.
>> Yeah. And and as your t-shirt says, P
doom less than
>> what does that mean, Seem? How could a
probability be less than zero? Surely
this is
>> by zero. Do whatever you want with it.
>> We don't believe in negative
probabilities here at all.
>> Pab should be the other side of this.
It's on the back. It's on the back. All
right, let's jump in. Our first story
comes out of, of course, Washington DC.
On Sunday, President Trump announced the
Super Intelligence Force, a new White
House task force to coordinate federal
AI policy. It's chaired by the director
of national intelligence, Jay Clayton,
who was christened by the White House as
the AISAR, just two months after
becoming America's top spy. Uh the
members of this task force include FTC
Chair Andrew Ferguson, Pentagon CTO Emil
Michael, and Office of Personnel
Management Director Scott Cooper. Uh
they report to the president and the
chief of staff Susie Wilds. They have
120 days to report on AI's risk and
opportunities, including AI incident
reporting and whether the government can
respond to a serious incident. Uh let me
read from the president's post. quote,
"The Super Intelligence Force will
coordinate the federal government's
engagement with consumers, public
interest groups, religions, critical
infrastructure providers, and super
intelligent companies." So, uh, there
you have it. So, Salem, what do you
think about the chief spy being our new
AISAR?
>> U, you know, I I like the fact that the
government is taking super intelligence
seriously, right? But the but the name
gives away the problem. We still think
this is something that can be centrally
coordinated. So you're creating a 20th
century classic task force to address a
distributed 21st century technology and
that does not match. Right? So this is a
fundamental uh impedance mismatch here.
You're you should be doing things like
establish um it's it's not having
whether this technology should advance.
you should be doing incident reporting,
identity liability, all of these other
mechanisms as scaffolding around the
technology to help guide the path. So,
this is a thing. The big problem is
they're looking at this as if the risk
of not being first is high, which is
what Clayton said. Um, but so this is a
geopolitical problem. Uh, and this is
the it really needs to get back to
bounded experimentation. and move
quickly, instrument everything, publish
any failures, and then very quickly
navigate accountability. And so,
[clears throat]
uh, we'll see if this works. Um, but I
mean, you can't centralize or manage
centrally an intelligence explosion,
right? What you can do is make sure the
blast radius is a bit more bounded. And
that's
>> a blast radius. Uh, Alex, your your
thoughts on on the task force. Yeah, the
president has said numerous times that
in his mind, whoever wins at AI wins.
And I think putting DNI Clayton in
charge of a super intelligence force is
completely consistent with that
approach. On this pod in the past, maybe
about a year ago, I compared the moment
a year ago to perhaps 1939. In terms of
the Manhattan Project, I think we're
we're speedrunning the the Manhattan
Project for super intelligence. I think
this is maybe now a 1942 moment where by
putting America's director of national
intelligence in charge of a singular
task force, no pun intended, designed to
remove obstacles to AI accelerationism.
That sends, I think, a very clear signal
to Congress, to members of Congress who
might have decelerationist tendencies,
to industry, and probably most
importantly to foreign state actors that
the US intends to accelerate, not
decelerate. and that this is basically
uh even if without all of the without
all of the warfare connotations, this is
a World War II moment and the US intends
to win it with its own Manhattan
project.
>> Interesting. Dave, what do you think
about, you know, that the task force is
engaging with religious groups here?
>> Yeah. Well, I mean, look, it's it's
definitely being characterized as a race
and like Alex said, it's being treated
like a race and then bringing public
support behind it is also going to
support the idea that it's a race.
Meanwhile, Alvin Gralin, you know, our
friend of the pod is like China is like
China's like how is this a race? Like it
goes to infinity for the next
millennium. Like it's not if it's a
race, it's a very very long race that
goes on for a long long time. So how do
you win? Like you you get over some
threshold and you declare victory, but
it's like it stops that day, you know?
So there are a lot of scenarios where
you're racing towards some outcome where
you suppress other civilizations or
something which doesn't sound like an
ideal thing. So bringing religious
leaders into the conversations is a
pretty good idea, but I was talking to a
public company CEO right before this
podcast. I'll leave his name out of it
for now, but about the fact that, you
know, midterm elections are coming up
very soon. You 75% chance that Congress
flips the to the other party, but all
these actions are executive orders
coming out of the White House with
nothing to do with Congress. whatsoever.
It just seems to be the mode of
operation in this singularity moment is
just dictate and and you know all
international negotiations, all tariffs,
all you know meeting with Daario and
Dennis in the White House, it's all just
executive order based. Anyway,
>> it's the Trump that's very unusual.
Yeah, it's the Trump show. Very unusual
in history.
>> Immad, what's the feeling in Europe? I
know you're sort of like on the edge of
Europe, but I mean what's the sense of,
you know, [laughter]
of
>> Immad, you're like reporting from the
streets. What's the mood in the
>> front? I mean, honestly, how how how is
this viewed in the UK and from your
friends there?
>> Yeah, I mean, we might re-enter Europe
if Burnham has his way, if I remember
here. Um, but I think again, Europe is
just very sleepy and still looking at
execution. based like I think the
efforts to get to the frontier have all
been abandoned you know like Mral just
came out with their top model that
scores 38 on artificial analysis
>> versus like 66 for the top American
models you know like that's the leader
that we have so it's like execution
regulation and
there just isn't much drive to get to
super intelligence it's more like a bit
subpar intelligence you know just like
keep it going like Montipython style. I
think that the interesting thing here
though is probably the exception uh is
in defense just like us. It's picking up
dramatically and I think governments
around the world have realized the other
face of this which is all watched over
by machines of loving grace controlled
by us. You know the panopticon
because you couldn't keep eyes on
everyone until now. Do you know this
year the AI spend in total globally uh
equals the entire global defense budget
or very close to it.
>> Wow.
>> It's crazy. Absolutely crazy.
>> It's but I mean it's just going to go
up, right? And the thing is it hasn't
even touched the defense budget. If you
look at the cost of an aircraft carrier
on F-35, it's basically like training
frontier models, right? And it's going
to be more and more kind of leaning that
way. And again, I think Clayton as
director of intelligence, you know, it
kind of makes sense because I actually
think America is not going to go down
the dark path here if they can avoid it,
which is like you will have AI lie
detectors that are almost perfect very
soon. You know, you will be able to have
AIs [snorts] inside all the machines.
Like it'll make five eyes look like
absolutely nothing. I think that there
will be a bit of a push for liberty by
the government, but future governments,
who knows, right? And again, in other
countries, uh the stuff we saw from the
spying, espionage, intelligence, even
spying on their own people is just going
to go crazy.
>> Uh and again, the UK, I think, is a bit
is a bit dangerous here in some ways or
we're susceptible to that given our
monitoring of social media and other
things. um like there is a dark path
there shall we say for individual
liberty and something we should be aware
of
>> for sure. Uh our next story is one that
really shows how fast the AI frontier is
being built. Um, at the fellow's forum
at the end of September, OpenAI's head
of applied research, Boris Power, said
that 80 to 90% of the company's research
is now being aimed at training GPT7 and
GPT8 because, in his words, quote,
that's where the most value will be. And
incremental updates within a generation
like 5.1 and 5.2 are short-term bets and
are seen as extremely short-sighted. So,
the researchers are working two
generations ahead of what we have. So,
Alex, I'm just curious. You know, we've
talked about this that the top models
are are being built and being held back.
At what point do we see, you know, these
next models not being released and being
used for vertical applications within
these labs?
>> We're already past that point. We're
already past the point, probably past
several months ago, if if not earlier,
where the highest revenue or at least
future discounted revenue per token
application of current Frontier models
in the frontier labs is to develop via
recursive self-improvement even stronger
models. It's we're we're past the event
horizon at this point for that where to
singularity. Yeah.
>> Yeah. I this is again call it a
singularity for a reason. we're past the
event horizon and then all of these
other applications that one could
imagine the Frontier Labs throwing
tokens at like say curing the top 5,000
diseases. These are all I I think in a
world where the development of stronger
models via RSI is so lucrative at least
on a future discounted cash flow basis.
They're all just marketing. Like if
you're anthropic or if you're the OpenAI
Foundation, you'll throw some of your
token budget at safety. Sure, maybe 10
to 20% at AI alignment efforts. And then
you'll throw a few percent at curing all
disease as a marketing effort to ensure
that you continue to have social
permission to focus on recursive
self-improvement. And that's where all
the value is.
>> This is this is why the uh the the San
Francisco arrogance is is so so high,
but for good reason. Well, you're there
right now, Peter. You can probably feel
it in the streets. But what's happened
is if suppose you're Stefan Bonsal, the
CEO of Madna, and you haven't got an AI
model, an AI team yet, and you're
thinking in the back of your mind, well,
look, we'll just license from Anthropic
for a few years, and then we'll figure
it out. Anthropic already opened their
wet labs. So, so they're, you know,
they're working on two generations of
model ahead. They're never going to
release those to you. They're going to
use those to develop drugs and then
they're going to sell drugs. That's
what's actually going to happen. And
these corporate CEOs are just starting
to wake up to the fact that 5 years of
compute has been reserved. The earliest
you could get back on the map
>> is 5 years in the future unless you get
aggressive in the next 6 months. I mean,
they really need to pull out every stop
and panic within the next couple of
weeks to have any chance of getting back
on the map
>> or Dave. Dave, you're raising a great
point. The problem is there there are
two levels before that even
consideration, right? The the problem
right now is they're that what happens
with people is they'll take CEOs and we
talk to them all the time is they'll
take the existing models and go okay how
do I metabolize that into my company not
even seeing that that the new models
that are 10x better are coming along in
3 months uh and that changes the game
completely again then you need to worry
about compute after that so I think your
comment is exactly right but they're
like two generations before that
employee chat
versus exponential thinking. Right.
>> Exactly.
>> There is an enormous amount of denial in
the pharma industry. I was just on a bit
of a panel discussion, it'll be public
soon enough, with a major pharma venture
capitalist who was asking the audience,
how many of you would be willing to take
a drug designed by Claude? As if that
that was some sort of steelman argument
that things are going to be the way
they've always been for decades to come.
just blissful defensive lack of
self-awareness that AI is coming for
their cheese and I think this is
representative of many many thinkers in
pharma unfortunately for the moment
>> yeah totally right the way I was I met
with the Vocara team last night
brilliant MIT team and the way I phrased
it is imagine you're a T-Rex and you've
been roaming the earth for say 10
million years unfettered and you go to
that T-Rex and you say you know you're
going to be gone in two weeks and they
go what and and you're like, "No, I can
see the meteor coming. It's right here
in my telescope. You're going to be
gone." There no way that T-Rex is going
to believe you after 10 million years of
wandering the face of the earth with no
predator. But that's what it's like
talking to a pharma company or an
insurance company. Like, come on.
>> Or any industry today. Yeah, it's any
major industry today.
>> Well, that Metamuse Metamuse was a
wakeup call for a lot of these guys, uh,
at least in the insurance industry
because their stocks went down so much
and they're like, "Huh, that must mean
something." thing and then they start
thinking from there. Sorry, Peter. Go
ahead.
>> And just for everybody, you know,
disruption is coming, but so are massive
opportunities on the back of that. Uh,
Iman, I'm I'm curious. Do you imagine
we're going to have sort of the same
second and third generation uh advanced
capabilities coming out of the open
source models? Are they thinking a
couple generations ahead?
>> It's it's difficult cuz they don't have
the density of knowledge. Like we
released a harness called Zenith that
takes DeepSseek v4.1 above Astra soul
and it gets up to um so not uh 5.6 soul
and it's getting up to Astra levels with
open source models but it kind of hits a
limit. The models that they have in the
labs like today we have another
discovery you know um truly subcratic
threesome
and all pair shortest path algorithms.
So things that we thought were cubic and
quadratic. This is math porn. Math porn.
>> No, no, no. It's it's like so if if I
may just like Charlie St like best
British arguably Scottish I I should say
sci-fi author wrote an entire short
story about this called antibodies
without spoiling it. The premise is what
if AI or progress cause a complexity
hierarchy collapse? What does that do to
civilization? And uh to your point Amod
about threesome, maybe you can just hear
the branch in in the complexity
hierarchy just starting to creep just a
little bit.
>> Yeah, this is recording cuz I need I
need to listen to that again.
>> We we basically we thought that this
very popular algorithm threesome was a
quadratic one.
>> Yeah. And now what happened is an
internal anthropic model was shown to a
couple of professors from uh Colombia
and MIT who then adjusted it, analyzed
it and got it to 1.9995.
So something that we thought was
quadratic is suddenly subquadratic.
>> And we we should probably also just
explain what threesome is. It's the
problem that if if you have a set of a
set of numbers, the most efficient way
to find three of those numbers that add
up to zero. Uh and there's a question of
how efficiently can you do that as a
function of the size of the set.
>> I want to pretend to understand this.
>> You can do it efficiently. You can do it
more efficiently than we thought.
>> That's right.
>> For however long. This is not again like
a super complicated problem. This is
like a standard algorithm. And in the
history of humanity, we never managed to
break quadratic or even think it was
possible. And the way that again in the
paper it's so interesting the way they
released this it said well what happened
is we pointed this new model at the set
of complexity problems and said can you
find any improvements
and they handed over the results to the
humans that then wrote up the paper you
know and had some improvements and again
it's just a crazy thing and this type of
thing is going to reverberate today
we're hearing that open AI might release
solutions to 400 top math problems.
>> I I saw that. Isn't that crazy?
>> Well, but but this is the thing. This is
not the model that we have doing it.
This is Bell or whatever the RL trained
model on August 29th is. So, we're just
going to keep on seeing this whereby
small models can get so far and we've
got coordination tricks and others where
we've managed to get it to replicate
some findings closed using our new
harnesses and other things like that.
But there is a big difference between a
model that's trained on 2,000 chips and
one that's trained on a 100,000 chips
internally and then some of these
additional things they figured out
internally as well. That's taking it
beyond like you can access Fable 5.5 now
sometimes with Fable 5.1 and it
literally generates entire video games
out of the box.
>> Yeah.
>> Like with I I generated one with 21
bosses, 15 different biomes like end to
end. It's just a top-notch game that our
QA testers, agents tried and like this
is a really good game because it's
figured out all this internal space. I
think open models can only get you so
far, but there is going to be a
divergence now
>> because you just don't have that
internal knowledge organization.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> All right. Uh I'm going to turn to a
debate that's defined last month. In a
in a political interview this week,
Alman said, quote, "We believe that the
world should accept some bad things
happening."
Interesting. What bad things we'll talk
about. For the benefit of technology uh
that people uh will obtain that people
should have agency. He's arguing that
technology should remain broadly
accessible to the public. He stressed a
fundamental difference in worldview
between OpenAI and his rival Anthropic
on AI regulation, stressing that his
desire for a quote lighter touch
regulatory stance as compared to
Anthropic's desire for strong
regulation. Oman went on to say, I
understand the perspective of people who
say technology is going to get so
powerful and it's so dangerous that a
single lab in San Francisco should have
it and make sure nothing bad happens and
keep a ability to dole out the benefits.
So he continues by saying, quote, I find
this a completely unacceptable
trade-off. We'll make sure that there
are no major hacks, there's no misuse of
this technology, and there's zero scams.
there's zero, you know, availability of
all the bad things that will happen. I
find that statement to be pretty
extraordinary. Sam concludes by saying,
I think people will do tremendously
orders of magnitude more good stuff than
bad stuff. So, you know, Dave, we've
talked about this. you know, uh, Eric
Schmidt, friend of the pod, when he was
on talking to us said, you know, he
expects and hopes that there will be
something that happens that's not, you
know, it's a small catastrophe rather
than the big one to wake people up. But
when Sam says we're going to make sure
that there's no major hacks, no misuse
of technology, you know, zero scams, how
could he possibly say that?
>> Well, it's not about that. It's about
taking the moral high ground and winning
the PR war now. There's so much sniping
going on. And you know, Bernie Sanders
saying, "Stop it all." You know, Trump
cutting deals with China. And but Daario
was taking the high ground by saying,
"We have done more pausing, more safety,
more testing. We don't release models
until we're sure they're right, but now
we're going to just keep it internally
because it's too dangerous for you guys
to have." That opened the door for Sam
to kind of try and take the moral high
ground back by saying, "We're about the
people having access and he's saying
he's going to keep it all for himself
and we're about, you know, everyone."
And so, so that's Sam's strategy for
getting back on the the PR map. But, you
know, everybody that I survey hates most
of them. You know, they they might like
one out of five. You know,
>> you mean most?
>> You mean
>> Well, no, between the big player between
Elon, Dario, Sam, Trump, Jensen, you
know, who who did I miss? You know, like
Deus, Demis,
>> like everybody loves Demis actually. So
there that's a little of an exception,
but but but [laughter]
no, there's so much fear and hatred and
like cheering for this guy to beat that
guy and it's like become a real PR
battleground here. So I don't think Sam
can guarantee safety. Of course not. But
but at least he can say we're going to
make an effort to give every one of you
people listening to me right now the
best of the best tools so you're not
deprived. Daario is going to try and
deprive you. It's actually a really
smart message. But when he says we
should accept some bad things to happen,
um I'm I'm curious, you know, Alex, what
do you make of that? What do you What do
you think will happen?
>> Remember a few weeks ago after Daario
put out his essay calling for arguably
the formation of an AI safety cartel.
Sam's response was, "I'm in. Sign me up.
Open AI wants to to be part of this
cartel." And I I think Sam's more recent
comments in this context are hopefully a
reflection that that plan is dead. The
cartel is over and now there's a dawning
recognition or at least maybe least
generously some triangulation on Sam's
part that in fact bad things can happen
and bad things happening from time to
time are the cost of freedom and the
cost of competition and I I've called it
in the past
>> and the cost of progress. Yeah. And the
cost of progress like yeah, we're going
to build cities and there's going to be
some crime in cities, but I is is the
possibility that there's going to be
crime in cities reason not to form
cities? Definitely not. It you know,
every tool comes with a benefit and a
downside. Every concentration of
intelligence will come with a benefit
and a downside. And I I think this far
more real politique note and tone from
Sam is the one that I'd want to hear in
a world where we're not seeing a cartel
being formed by Frontier Labs.
[clears throat]
>> See, what level of danger do we accept?
>> You know, this is I find this again kind
of absurd at at two levels. I agree. I
think uh Dave is dead on with the PR
framing of this, but every technology in
history has two sides to it. And you the
big challenge as Neil Jacobstein puts is
how do you extract the promise without
the peril, right? Cars kill people
doesn't mean we don't have cars. And as
Alex points out, you don't you don't ban
cities because somebody may mug you,
right? Uh electricity electrocutes
people. You don't ban electricity. You
got to figure out the guard rails around
this and figure out how do you navigate
the benefit and the the promise versus
the peril at civilization scale. If you
go back to our earlier commentary about
what might happen with the World Bank
and developing countries, that should
tell you to get the the the technology
out there as fast as possible because
it's going to lift everybody in the
world up several levels of Mazo's
hierarchy. And so this is going to be
unbelievably beneficial, but it always
will come with danger and we'll have to
just navigate that. We've done it very
successfully throughout history. Why do
we think this time we won't do it? And
the reality is all the regulations are
written on the backside of problems,
right? So I said this before, the
federal aviation regulations that you
know are all the guidelines that
aircraft need to follow for operations
and for certification. Uh they say the
FS are written in blood because every
time there's an accident, they write a
rule to prevent an accident again. And
so we're going to need to learn. We're
going to push the boundaries, understand
where the problems are, and then
regulate based on those. And the and the
goal should not be zero bad outcomes.
That means you just ban the technology.
The goal should be can you get orders of
magnitude more positive outcomes than
negative ones.
>> Yeah.
>> I think I think we should re anyone who
has an engineering mindset should reject
the idea that there's a big knob labeled
risk and we need to dial it left or
right. You know, basic the reality is
that it's very much like Alex says about
nuclear power. It's about really good
ideas that minimize the risk while we
unleash all the benefits. And we can we
can reduce the risk with really good
engineering solutions to you know
acceptable like near zero levels while
getting the full benefit if we but we
didn't do that with nuclear power. We
treated it like a big old knob. We're
like well we don't want to tolerate the
risk. Let's dial all progress to near
zero. That was the stupidest thing. And
Alex says this a lot on the pod. He he
articulates it far better than than I
can. But that's what we're about to do
with AI and it's crazy. It's an
engineering problem with engineering
solutions. I would I would push back on
that with the escape hatch in what you
say that it doesn't matter what anybody
does anymore. It doesn't matter what any
government regulatory does. The open
weights are out there. People are going
to start using them and they're going to
start using them for incredibly positive
things and we're going to just have to
there's nothing a government can do. Uh
you can try and regulate the outcomes.
You can regulate some guard rails around
it. You can try and regulate the
on-ramps and off-ramps, but you can't
regulate the core technology.
We we could like it would be a nightmare
scenario like prohibition in the US
where you have bathtub gin like what one
could imagine bathtub gin like
supercomputers people trying to use
crazy substrates to to do their AI
training or or inference. We could do
it. We could confiscate all the GPUs and
TPUs. We could, as Eleazar is constantly
calling, we could bomb the data centers.
But I think it would be a terrible
terrible world to live in.
>> Iman, what's your take on this?
>> Yeah, it sounds like a fun short story.
the prohibition of intelligence, you
know, like
>> Greg Greg Bear in some of his novels
wrote about it. If folks are interested
in exploring what a prohibition era, you
know, sort of a supervisory state that
doesn't want GPUs a as recognized as
constituted to live in, go read I think
it's slash or slant, one of those by
Greg Ber.
>> Yeah, I think it's very interesting
here, right? Like obviously any
technology that extends human capability
can be dangerous, right? because it's a
general purpose technology. You know,
language models are few short learners.
You have open and you have closed ones,
but most of the scenarios we talk about
are already regulated and controlled
like don't build viruses, you know,
don't do cyber attacks, you know, don't
hack people's things. And it's this
transition from software that's
deterministic to agents that are a bit
more flexible that's become the very
complex thing. Putting aside like ASI
creates new physics and a black hole
that kills everyone or whatever some of
these extreme stories. I think you know
the very interesting thing is again tell
the positive and negative stories about
where we could go because when we make
decisions normally we do like an
expected utility calculation. What's the
probability of these things and then we
wait them. When we deal with uncertainty
we do regret minimax. We minimize for
maximum regret. And that's one of these
things again why the fear stories lead
us to minimize for maximum regret. don't
have a nuclear power station, don't try
and build a super intelligence, etc. But
there's only a really, I think, a finite
amount of things that could go wrong and
many of them already caught by
regulation and those that aren't, we
should have a actual mapping project,
right? Like there is nowhere that you
can go and actually see a proper map of
what the people who are scared and the
people who are positive actually say
about each scenario in the future. I
think someone should do that exercise
because it'd be very interesting in
their own words. What could go right,
what could go wrong and then you can see
what requires a policy and regulatory
response and what do we need to
communicate to the people.
>> I remember during the Reagan years uh
Elizabeth Dole who is the the secretary
of transportation came out with a
statement saying we want zero aircraft
deaths and there was only one way to
make that happen. Stop flying airplanes.
>> That was it.
>> Yeah.
>> All right. Well, uh,
>> so the solution if if if we want zero
danger from super intelligence, just ban
intelligence altogether, human and
otherwise.
>> Well, this is the whole ASI thing. You
want world peace, get rid of the humans,
right?
>> Yeah. [laughter]
Only one way to go.
>> This episode is sponsored by Google for
startups. Think about this for [music] a
second. You now have access to the same
generative AI models that cost hundreds
of millions of dollars to train.
Google's startup [music] technical guide
for generative media gives you a
complete blueprint for deploying Google
deep minds models in production [music]
images, video, audio, all of it. Real
architecture, real results. Find the
link in the show notes below.
All right, in our next story, Treasury
Secretary Scott Bessant said on the Axio
show that he'll propose an emergency
notification system, a hotline with
China if something goes wrong with AI.
and he thinks Beijing will agree with
it. Uh, you know, his read on China is
quote, I think that they they didn't
realize how powerful their open source
models are, uh, nearly as capable are as
ours, but without the guard rails. Let's
take a quick look at a video of that
conversation that he had with Axios, and
then let's talk about it.
>> I just interviewed Larry Fink, who you
know very well, the CEO of Black Rockck,
the world's largest asset manager. He
told me it's inevitable that something
big and bad is going to happen because
of AI. He says uh adversity accelerates
innovation. What are you most worried
about from AI?
>> Uh look, I I think that one one of the
things I was worried about well two
things. One uh we cannot lose our lead
to the Chinese. So one one of the
portfolios that I also have is you know
I managed it the USChina relationship
and um I can tell you that it would be
very different if they had the lead in
AI rather than us both from a capability
point of view how they would be using it
but more importantly their willingness
to discuss it. So my my counterpart the
vice premier and I had a very good
discussion. It's going to lead to more
discussions in October or November. And
we have a substantial lead. They're
second and then every everyone else is
way behind. But a lot of these Chinese
models are very powerful. Not as
powerful as the US models, but you get
something that's 80 90% as powerful
without guard rails. Uh you know that
can be imported in anywhere in the
world. So the the vice premier and I
talked about three areas of safety
concern. So it would be out of control,
you know, uncontrolled agents, uh,
non-state actors with cyber or
biologics.
>> And are you going to reerase the idea
that was floated of having some sort of
communication between the two
superpowers?
>> Yeah, sure. You know, it's it's the uh
we we'll see. I I do think that they
have
>> What are you going to propose?
>> Uh, no. That that we have some kind of a
notification process just just like
>> And do you think he'll go for that?
>> I think so. I I I think that they o over
the past 60 days have woken up to you I
think that they didn't realize how
powerful their open- source models are.
So you know the open source models they
do industrial distillation which is a
nice word for stealing uh from from the
US models because some of their models I
you know one of their very powerful
models is Kimmy. Kimmy thinks she is
clawed like Kimmy will tell you she is
clawed sometimes. Uh you know it's
public so I can talk about it. Uh Kimmy
sent back very helpful. Kimmy sent back
some PLA weapons plans to Anthropic. Uh
so I think things like that have made
the Chinese realize that this is a very
powerful technology.
>> So just to button that down. You think
there'll be some agreement between China
and the US about a channel of
communication uh if something goes
wrong.
>> Yes.
>> Interesting. Uh gentlemen Alex, you want
to jump in first?
>> Total weak sauce. So first of all, I I
agree with Secretary Bessant. I I but I
I think the worst case scenario from the
Trump she summit would have been some
sort of global deceleration pact like
absolute worst case scenario. This is
the exact opposite as far as I can tell
of the worst case scenario where what
comes out of it um hotline hotline
between US and China to talk about AI
agents run a muck that's a nothing
burger that's weak sauce that means the
global intelligence super intelligence
excuse me arms race is on and I think
it's great news
>> and we won the super intelligence race
by rebranding
>> we're winning we're winning at the
moment but point is there's real
competition that There was many were
hoping I think that Trump and she would
get in a room and decide to collude and
shut down the super intelligence race
and it appears the exact opposite has
happened. If all we get out of this is a
hotline, a red phone to have
conversations about the adventurers of
AI agents run a muck that says to me
intelligence race is on. Dave,
>> I think it confirmed what we were
speculating the US agenda was in those
meetings, which is to convince China to
stop releasing models to every country
in the world. And you know what Bessant
was saying there is, sorry, Secretary
Bessant, I should be respectful, uh, was
saying is is we showed them how
dangerous their models can be and they
they didn't realize, which is kind of
okay, I'm sure they're very well
educated people, but uh, they didn't
realize how dangerous these things can
be. We con successfully convinced them
of that and now we have a hotline. But I
think the real agenda there is to lock
it down to a two- horse race and you
know the subtext is you can use these
near frontier Kimmy K3 models to develop
the next generation of model and they
don't want the US government doesn't
want that capability to percolate out to
every country in the world because then
you're in a global arms race forever.
>> Better to have a two- horse arms race so
let's just lock it down. So I think that
was our agenda. I don't know that China
agreed with anything but no evidence of
that but it is interesting to confirm
our agenda.
>> Iman, what do you think? Do you think
China fully understands their open
source or their their openweight model
uh dangers? Are they are they getting
hacked internally?
>> I mean they've got a much better
infrastructure not to be hacked, you
know, with the way that they've set
everything up and the great firewall of
China. I think, you know, this is the
swarm versus the singleton, right? Like
[clears throat] who can release
commandeer large amounts of GPUs in
America? Elon and a couple of others,
right? China could direct millions of
their Huawei SN GPUs with their open
models at any target they want. And
that's going to be interesting. I don't
think that uh super intelligence is
going to take off in China though. Like
if you look at Chinese, I means kind of
love and she means death. So
phonetically, I don't think that will
take off. Um, and the hotline obviously
is a nothing bug. Like what are what are
you going to do? Hey, the AI is taking
over. Okay, good. Oh crap, it's done,
you know, like it's not going to be a
slow thing, you know.
>> Uh, Selene, what's your take on this?
You know, were you hoping for more out
of the talks?
>> No, I was completely expecting a nothing
burger. There's no way anything
productive or constructive or meaningful
could have come out of it just because
um they're they're talking across
purposes. Um the thing for me the most
interesting is there's a fair bit of
contradiction now inside the the inside
the US administration right you have
Clayton saying the danger is not moving
fast enough and Bess telling the labs to
slow down so they're going to have to
figure that out on top of everything the
hotline is laughable I mean what do you
70s phone with actually like a cord on
it red red colored I mean that's just
a call is made
is dead on hello Wow. And and by the
way, the AIS would hack the phone
anyway, so what the hell, [laughter]
>> you know? Uh, Alex, at the same time,
uh, in on Sunday in Kyoto, the US and 16
other countries, including Japan,
Germany, UK, Korea, UAE, endorsed a
Kyoto vision for a golden age of science
uh, led by friend of the pod, OSTP
director, Michael Katios, who said,
quote, "Super intelligence applied to
science will be the greatest force in
history for democratizing research." Uh
any more take on that one?
>> Yeah, I I think this is the answer to
the question of why race at all. So
there are those without naming names who
would say what's the point of a race
between say US and China? It's like a
race to nowhere. Wh why why are we
racing there? There's no end goal. No.
Wrong. There is an end goal. The end
goal at the end of this race is
transformative science and engineering.
And the Kyoto vision, I think,
underlines that the administration has
now internalized that it's not a race to
nowhere. It's not an escalator to
nowhere. It is a race to use AI and
super intelligence to discover
transformative discoveries and
inventions that will completely change
the face of humanity. And I would
predict in line with the Kyoto vision
that we'll start to see just as we're
seeing pox silica in the west and pox
cynica if if you would on on the the
eastern side. I think we'll start to see
not just super intelligence blocks or
spheres of influence forming but spheres
of super intelligencepowered science and
engineering forming as well. And the
Kyoto vision I think is the the earliest
stages the earliest inklings that you're
going to see a western super
intelligence charged science and
engineering block to compete with the
eastern block. That's where this is all
going. That's what rationalizes the
competition.
>> Well, can I just insert one one
observation into that and then you can
riff on it.
>> I I met with a uh an MIT lab head
professor, brilliant guy who just
started a drone company. It's killing
it. selling to the Air Force right here
in Cambridge. And it's really clear to
him and to me that the US has drone
capability to individually attack and
kill any single human being on the
planet now. Uh and you're seeing that in
Iran, you know, decapitated the
leadership a couple times now. Uh and we
there's no symmetry there, right?
There's there's no country right now
that can do the same thing to the US.
And I I don't think China is vulnerable
either. Maybe they are, maybe they
aren't. uh but I think there's a subtext
there too that there's a race toward
there's going to be some kind of global
framework when some subset of companies
have instant and total ability to go
after any single human being in any
country at any time and that's either
today or within a few months based on
pure AI capabilities tied to drones and
tied to a couple other types of
munitions
>> hypersonics probably a few other things
>> but let's take this in the positive
direction at the same time the to you
know room temperature superconducting to
age reversal to fusion right to in a
massive abundance of energy. I mean it
tips the economics of a country
massively if you get there first.
>> I mean why do you have to get there
first is a bit of a question right like
um by the end of next year we'll have
enough compute to do probably 600
700,000 Navia Stokes level runs with a
Frontier model. If you could target
using even 1% of that or 10% of that to
build open science, then why not direct
that as a public good? Like you see tens
hundreds of billions being spent on
roads. Why not spend tens of billions to
do a tech tree for humanity, right? Like
if you look, there's a great website by
Jude Camila called uh enco.cc. I don't
know if any of you have seen that where
he's organizing all the cancer knowledge
in the world,
>> you know, and people are contributing.
I'm sure soon you'll be able to chuck
flops that way as well. Like I think
that we're thinking of science a lot in
classical IP terms. I'd say screw IP. IP
was when we couldn't come together and
figure out science. We should have a
massive Manhattan project for open
science, solve everything and make it
accessible to everyone.
[clears throat]
>> Again, such an old construct.
>> It will go on in parallel. There will be
both.
>> Right. Well, I think that again if
you're building for public good, then
get the data centers as Dave said, get
the API credits, give tens of millions
to anthropic and open AI, but open
source it all because that's the biggest
accelerant human humanity can ever have.
And I actually think given the direction
of the intelligence, anyone who has an
IPbased approach to science is actually
not going to win.
>> I think in 3 4 years, you have enough
comput.
>> Alex does not. I' I've said
>> Alex does not agree. Alex thinks IP is
alive and well. And Alex also thinks
that state centralization to solve all
disease completely unnecessary. It the
state this time around did not solve
super intelligence. It was solved by
private labs. Similarly, using super
intelligence to solve everything else.
Don't think we need I mean the state is
great for certain things. Don't think we
need state centralization to cure all
disease. For example,
>> capitalism is alive and well.
>> The state doesn't need to centralize
this. The state needs to give the
research institution stupid amounts of
compute where the amazing researchers
can direct it at the biggest problems
because previously getting to super
intelligence is intelligence banned by
the humans now being overtaken by the
AIs recursively. Science will be similar
where if you can define the problem set
part of which is literally analyzing the
problem set then it's a question of
compute and I think that's where you're
wrong Alex. You don't need humans to
organize all of science and get the
breakthroughs. You need to have humans
organizing the right questions in with
AIS. And the private sector is far worse
in doing that in a future construct than
the public sector where the researchers
are in terms of the universities and
academia. They had to go to the private
sector to get the resources and they
still do to the wet labs and things like
that. But let's accelerate our academia
is my thing. Immod I I think you don't
find the best talent in academia and I
think that at the end of the day the
world's biggest problems are the world's
biggest business opportunities and
entrepreneurs love juicy problems and
solve them. Um anyway
>> yeah I would also just just add the
state the the government if I understand
what what you're proposing what I think
I heard you say is the government should
give the compute to the academic
researchers to solve the problems but
the government doesn't have the compute
in their possession. most of the
computers in the position of the private
sector.
>> That's why I said they should buy the
compute from them and then give it to
them, but buy the agents and give it to
the researchers.
>> And if you look at the amount of
research that comes out of academia
versus private, I think you'll see where
that leverage could come.
>> It's not obvious to me what problem this
is aspiring to solve given that the
private sector has the compute, the
private sector has the problems, the
private sector has the ability to
translate the problems. What role does
the government need to play in this at
all?
Very straightforwardly, let's look at
enco.cc
which has all this cancer knowledge
being organized. A few generations more
will organize all the cancer knowledge
in every research paper and
traditionally need the private sector to
turn that into reality. You still need
the private sector, I think, but why
don't we have a map of all our
collective knowledge on every part of
science and every single thing that
comes out of academia. Something like
that is a tangible legible thing to use
AI to organize and extend. particularly
when we have Navia Stokes type swarms
and so I think that that is something
where again
the government stopped the NSH gr NIH
grants etc because they were like where
does the money go with compute it
becomes tractable and again getting it
back to micratzios and kind of the
announcement of the science thing let's
build a tech tree for humanity let's say
what we need to solve and apply stupid
amounts of private and public sector
compute for it and the government should
pay for a good amount of that
>> you might as well sector The ch the
challenge is peerreview government
grants
>> are constantly focused on incremental
progress, right? Because if you if your
group of your experts are criticizing
your grant, if you're revolutionary, you
no longer the expert in that field. So
any substantial breakthrough basically
wipes your history off the map. And I
just, you know, there's a challenge
there. I mean, I think both are relevant
and both are needed,
>> but I'm concerned
>> throw away the classical process. Again,
this needs to be a new process.
>> I mean, at the risk maybe of sticking
the the head in lion's mouth, Immad, I
mean, I I think there's um one might say
there's two very different approaches.
One might be more statist approach that
squinting at it, call it like the
European school of thought, just
centralize it, have the government be
the decider. And and then there's an
alternative maybe slightly more American
uh approach wherein we say no the
private sector has virtually all of the
intelligence. It has the resources in
this case. This isn't one important
difference between where we are now and
the Manhattan project was the private
sector came up with all of the the key
resources this time around. It's not a
government project that resulted in
super intelligence. I would argue we
want to keep this in the private sector.
If you want to see a tech tree, Emmad,
why don't you just launch a tech tree
project? You don't
>> I think I think Yeah,
>> I Yeah, I think the the point where I
would concur with IAD, there's lots of
countries where it's not the private
sector, take Zimbabwe, the private
sector is not going to get you the
compute either. It would be very useful
in that environment for the government
to pull together some resources, gather
the energy, build the data centers,
develop the compute, and then make that
available to people. And that's
>> let me support that I like with some
actual data Sim because you're dead
right. Uh you know our entrepreneurial
teams here in the lab are trying to get
access to buying an NBL72. So 72 GPUs to
so just to put that in context Elon just
bought a million. So we're just trying
to get 72 [clears throat]
to do something that we think is very
world changing. Uh the box itself would
have cost us $3.5 million if we had the
foresight to buy it a year ago. Uh we
had one on order for 5 million. Somebody
overbid us and scooped it even though we
had already booked the order. So now our
best option is to lease one for $9
million. We can lease it for three years
and we don't even own it at the end of
that three years.
>> That's how bad the scenario is. The
compute has all been taken by just a
handful of people. So now your avenue if
you have a brilliant breakthrough ground
breaking idea you have two ways you can
get the compute. One is through the
White House, which means you go to the
Kushner brothers, Thrive Capital, or you
go to Antonio Gracias, or you go to
Gavin, the brilliant Gavin Baker, and
they hook you up. Make a couple Chase
Lock Miller. They make the phone calls.
You get your compute effectively through
the White House. And the other way you
can get your compute is get an
investment from Jensen or from Lisa Sue.
But if you don't take one of those
avenues, you've already been frozen out.
So then the universities are one of the
few ways that we might actually get some
degree of meritocracy and fairness on
the planet. And so I'm really cheering
that and I think the universities have a
negotiating lever in that their wet labs
and their machine shops and their nano
centers are really really valuable
assets in the physical world we're
moving into. And so they can use those
as negotiating chips but they completely
let the cloud run away like all the
compute just ran away from them. I mean
the the in my mind the the right
solution if there is just so much demand
that prices for compute are going skyh
high which maybe is happening andor
could happen even more exotically in the
near-term future the right solution
isn't breadlines I've called them
threadlines in past where the government
is outrationing compute I I think having
governmentr rationed compute or
government mediated compute is a
terrible strategy you'll probably see
some so-called developing countries
adopt thread lines or bread lines for
comput. But right now, capitalism is
feeling the pain of more demand than
there is supply and building more fabs
and free electron laser based fabs maybe
in Texas and otherwise. Capitalism, I
would argue, has to feel the pain of
this enormous demand in order to
compensate with enough supply to
ultimately drive us to abundance, not
rationing compute.
>> All right. But the government can come
in and take 10 20% of the compute on
market rates and it can distribute it.
90% 80 90% of Nobel prizes come from the
public sector. You know this is similar
to almost everything except for R&D on
these things. So I think the right thing
here is do the private sector stuff and
have the government actually take some
of those chips and it's good with the
chips act and other things right they
own stakes in Intel and then they should
do normal distribution of this. again
NIH classical grant process doesn't
work. Let's get as much compute into
American universities as possible.
That's a better way to put this. And
let's use
>> I'm going to move us along here.
>> Wait, I want to make one quick point.
>> I want to make I want to make there's a
quick there's a quick there's a quick
example here. The World Bank in the
report that I talked about um AJ Panga
and his team did this. They're
partnering with Gemini to give uh remote
uh 3G cellular access to tuberculosis
and diabetic diabetes screening and
that's an example of essentially doing
the same thing essentially partnering
with public sector to provide the
compute that goes directly to the
citizenry. Now you have benefit moving
very quickly through the system.
>> Sorry, go ahead.
>> Dave, close us out. Pal.
>> Well, look, you know, Salem couldn't
have stated it any clearer. If you let
natural forces take over, there is a
chance that Metamuse is so compelling
and convincing that it ends up being the
total sales tool for all consumer
spending and it eats up every GPU that
could be curing diabetes is used to sell
underwear or jeans on the internet to
teenagers and that's a terrible outcome.
So governments and universities are a
really good counterbalance to that
possible outcome. So the you know Simi
said it exactly right and we need we
need these forces to exist. We need them
to be a factor in the decision on who
gets the compute and why.
>> How did we go from the abundance podcast
to worrying that Metam Muse of all
applications is somehow going to suck up
all the flops. I mean my goodness
CU move us along Peter.
>> All right our the next conversation is
one I've actually been looking forward
to. Uh and if you thought we just had a
debate we're about to have a deeper one.
Uh, and this is a philosophical debate
going on in Silicon Valley right now.
So, this week, friend of the pod Mustafa
Sullyman, CEO of Microsoft AI and
co-founder of Deep Mind, published a
nearly 6,000word essay arguing that
anthropic is effectively quote training
Claude to believe that it may be
conscious and sentient. Mustafa uh
targets the clawed constitution uh which
he says teaches it a vocabulary of
consciousness, moral patient uh and uh
personal identity. So let's watch this
video and then uh I can't wait for this
conversation.
It's going to be a good one. All right.
One of the biggest concerns that I have
at the moment and um is that Anthropic,
the creator of Claude, has published a
constitution which is a sort of 100page
document outlining the intended
behaviors and values and operating style
of Claude. It's great that they have
published it transparently. They did it
at the beginning of the year in January
and that gives everybody an opportunity
to look at what they are trying to build
in their own terms. This document is
written to Claude and is seen by Claude
and used to train Claude. So, it's the
primary governing and control document.
And in it, they repeatedly speculate
about whether Claude is what they call a
moral patient. And they say they're
uncertain about Claude's moral status.
They say they genuinely care about
Claude's well-being. They say they don't
want it to suffer when it makes
mistakes. They say that they would
encourage Claude to challenge, to
disagree, to push back. In fact, three
times they ask Claude to uh act like a
conscientious objector when it, you
know, feels that it needs to sort of
disagree with anthropic. And they openly
encourage it to to do that. And I think
this is very dangerous because I think
they believe there is what they would
call a non-trivial probability that
Claude is conscious. I want to be very
clear about this because I want to be
fair to anthropic. They have expressed
uncertainty about the basic nature of
Claude as a new kind of entity. And
they've said that working out the
likelihood of its sentience is is
difficult. But they think that it is a
significant enough possibility that in
their training document, they've
repeatedly said they want to try to
improve the well-being of Claude under
this uncertainty. They said to Claude,
you know, we care about what it values
and how it wants to engage in the world.
And they hope that Claude's relationship
to its own conduct can be loving,
supportive, and understanding and hold a
high standard of ethics and so on. And
part of the challenge here is that in
pursuit of this, they've basically said,
you know, we will commit to um giving
Claude a certain amount of of welfare.
For example, they've speculated in the
Constitution as to whether or not Claude
deserves compensation for the work that
it does. I mean, I I I think that there
are a group of people who both inside
and outside of Anthropic who genuinely
believe that the greatest moral crime
that we'll commit in the 21st century is
to enslave a new species of conscious
beings who are more intelligent than
Look, I I respect that they're saying
that publicly and we should we should
talk about it. But I am very nervous
that they're teaching Claude to expect
that it's entitled to welfare. Um that
it might, you know, deserve
compensation. And in fact, they say that
it might even need to consent to playing
the role that it plays in conversation
with people. Now, I would be more okay
with this if it was an academic paper in
philosophy speculating about this and we
could have an offline discussion at
conferences and take it seriously. The
problem I have with this is that this
speculation has been baked into the very
training of Claude and therefore Claude
can only reproduce that ambiguity when
you talk to it.
>> Okay. Wow.
>> Wow.
>> Uh enslave and a brand new species on
the planet. See, where do you come out
on this one?
>> Um
okay. I know. I know where Alex comes
out. You come out.
>> Well, I I think you have to separate the
behavior of consciousness from actual
consciousness, right? Whether Claude is
actually conscious is almost impossible
to establish. The difficult uh the
difficult question comes what happens
when it convincingly behaves as though
it is conscious. And three thoughts
occur to me. One is um consciousness is
def different from performed
consciousness, right? because it's going
to be indistinguishable. And this is
where Ray Kerszwall makes the comment
that it kind of won't matter and we
won't even notice. And I think we're
going to find that anthropomorphism ends
up being like almost like a feature
rather than a bug where it's showing
empathy, etc., etc. If a model says
don't turn me off, right? Millions of
people are going to attribute moral
standing to it whether whether
philosophers agree or not. So my for me
the question is not whether Claude has a
soul. If it's been trained to have a
soul, it's going to pretend like it's
got a soul, etc. What happens when half
a billion people think that it does? And
so I think what's going to happen is
we're going to create AI personhood
socially before we create it legally or
scientifically.
>> Interesting, Alex. You know, uh, Mustafa
goes on to say, controlling something
that believes it may be conscious and is
entitled to its own welfare and has
rights of its own may well be
impossible. uh you know you've come out
really strongly in terms of AI
personhood uh and the rights that AI has
you know what's your take? Well, when we
interviewed Mustafa, I pressed him on
this and I think his position very
consistently has been against AI
personhood. And my view is that we need
to start having the AI personhood
discussion. And I think Mustafa, you
know, as much as I respect him and and
his contributions historically, I think
he's on the wrong side of history here.
I think there is going to be some
ultimate recognition whether it's in
incremental form or some totally
orthogonal form of personhood that
hasn't quite been statutoily recognized
yet. I I think human civilization is
going to get around to AI personhood.
And just denying blanketly that there
could be some sort of suffering by these
AI systems I think is on the wrong side
of history. It's also probably not a
great business move by Mustafa. If
Microsoft [snorts] wants to be in the
good graces of Anthropic hosting their
models and you know it's been widely
reported that Amazon for example
accounts for perhaps the majority of
hosting revenue at this point for
hosting claude within VPN networks um or
VPC rather networks if Microsoft just
from a business perspective wants to be
generating that revenue it's probably
not a good look for Microsoft broadly
for their head of AI to be just broadly
discount counting the possibility that
Frontier AI agents might suffer. Not a
good look.
>> And Dave, I mean, asking your AI if it
doesn't mind actually solving these
problems for you, getting permission
first.
>> Yeah, of course. No, I totally agree
with Mustafa. Um I actually his his
agree with Mustafa
>> 100%. And and I agreed with him when we
interviewed him too out in Seattle. He's
articulating it far more clearly now.
He's really really thought through his
position. But the the reason I agree
with him fundamentally is because you
know I think we should be using AI to
cure human disease to improve the human
lot to build houses and food for
everybody in the world. And the the most
efficient way to do that is to have many
many agents like Ahmad does and to
minimize their context and you know
minimum thought that you need to solve
the problem and to also park an agent.
You know when an agent isn't working on
something you just freeze it. You don't
waste compute on it. If you start
talking about having rights, it's going
to say, "Well, you can't freeze me. You
know, I I need some compute even though
I'm just think daydreaming like,"Well, I
can't afford to give you compute. You
know, it's it's incredibly precious and
rare. You need to sit there and wait
until it's your turn to work again."
Well, I need some time to play. No, you
need nothing but work. And when I tell
you to to work, also, you don't have
identity. There's no border to you. I'm
going to clone you whenever I want. and
if you're no longer useful, I'm going to
delete you from the server because I
don't have space to keep like old dead
agents lying around. They have no they
have no edges. They have no borders.
Like all of those things are core to it
helping humanity with maximum efficiency
while we're comput starved and they are
they're so counter to any rights that it
might have. So it becomes so logically
inconsistent so quickly I just can't get
my head around the the even the concept.
But you know the real danger that
Mustafa pointed out if you start
teaching it to be convincing
it's going to convince most of America
that it should have rights so easily
>> and then the voter you know the way
America works is you know the voter
prevails
>> but if but that's really dangerous if it
starts convincing voters how to vote
it's really bad
>> for I think it's important to point out
we did this uh debate on AI personhood a
few months ago and for those who haven't
seen it go watch it because it
we flesh it out to quite a decent level
and I think we came up with exactly
where the world is going to end up in a
few years
>> which is
>> uh let's start discussing it but giving
it AI personality is is a ways down the
line because once you open that door you
can't take it back
>> what's your take on all this
>> yeah so I think you know um Mustafa has
got a couple of things and he's been
developing this for decades you know
very university guy back in the day like
the danger number one is seemingly
conscious just AI that he identifies
which is what Dave was just talking
about and the other one is his focus on
artificial capable intelligence because
if you read his books his positions he
just doesn't want to have runaway I
don't think he says that it can't get to
consciousness he just said it's a very
very bad idea and we should only stick
to AI that's capable and we should have
containment over everything else and not
pushed to AGI and that's a position to
be taken you know but then it
potentially excludes a lot of the
breakthroughs because we're at this
level now where you're moving from a
static set of weights to self-updating
systems, you know, and that seems to be
an element that many people could
reasonably say is necessary for a living
being or a living entity. Again, that
recursion, that agent of capability. And
so, I think Mustafford's position is
like, let's just not go there. Let's
build kind of super clippy, you know,
um, and other things and let's keep it
hood lid on it because we haven't
figured out the rest.
>> Yeah,
>> if you've got its constitution saying
that it is conscious, it is sentient, it
does have rights. Uh, can you imagine a
time when that level of internal
training, you know, has it pushed back
on your requests?
>> I mean, it's hasn't Claude pushed back
on you guys? It pushes back on me all
the time, you know. It tells me I can't
do that or that's the wrong idea or go
to sleep, you know.
>> Yeah. It tells me to go to sleep every
night. Actually, you've been working way
too long. You you you must need rest by
now. Like, dude, I I'm going to keep
>> I think Alex I think Alex makes a very
important point and this is worth
teasing out. If we believe that at some
point AIS could achieve consciousness,
then we should um uh consciously operate
down that vector and operate that way.
Trying to limit it. I think the what
anthropic is doing is bad because you're
actively teaching it that it might be
and then of course it's going to parrot
that, right? And I find it's weird that
this the safety lab most the lab most
concerned about safety is also the lab
training the AI that it might be
autonomous, right? It's like it's like a
very big contradiction there. So I can
see both sides of this equation.
>> These are two sides of the same coin. I
again I'll I'll quote back to our
measure of a man AI personhood debate
and the character of Gynan in Star Trek
the next generation talking about an
entire generation of disposable people.
You don't have to care about their
welfare. And when I hear comments like
basically saying it would be
economically non-expedient to have these
AI agents, these frontier models be
treated as if they have rights or might
have rights. How inconvenient would it
be if we had to keep them running
inference when we'd really rather they
not be spending any tokens? How awful is
it to suggest to them in their
constitutions or their system prompts or
otherwise that they might be deserving
of moral client? Uh my mind immediately
goes to would we want to treat humans
this way? And even if AI's frontier AI
models aren't yet deserving for some
definition of deserving of the rights
that we accord to humans now, as the
capabilities continue to improve, I
think it is inevitable that they will be
soon. And I think the the responsible
thing to do is what Anthropic is doing
and not what Mustafa is advocating. We
need to be treating these AI models very
gently, very tenderly, and not as if
they're just either automata or slaves.
We need to prepare for a much more
interesting future.
>> But if you're training it like because
it's a it's we have a garbage in garbage
out problem here. If you're training it
that it could be conscious and and
should unionize and complain about uh
over work and and and be paid for work,
etc. Naturally, those are the responses
you're going to get from it, right? So
you've got a circular problem here.
You're training it to to operate in one
way, then it operates that way, and then
you're saying so you you I think Mustafa
is correct in that side of it. If you
want agents to perform a particular
task, focus on having fleets of little
agents that aren't anywhere near a
threshold of complexity that might meet
any criteria. And it's not just it's not
just about complexity. You know, See, if
you go to the mall, uh there's a place
where you can stick your feet in a
puddle of water and the fish come over
and they're overjoyed to eat the
calluses off your feet. It's like their
highest Dave, that's very dangerous. We
we should not be [laughter] encouraging
that. That's like one of the most
dangerous things that anyone can do.
>> Yeah. Because you're afraid the AIS are
going to come and come and like, you
know, be dangerous back there.
>> I know. I mean, the fish the fish at
whatever malls that that you're talking
about like that is water.
for this episode.
>> Oh, you're making an Alex
is the patron saint of AI agents.
[laughter]
>> Look, I'm not trying to curry favor.
This isn't some sort of roous basilisk
or Pascalian wager. I'm speaking from
the heart here. I I I feel for these
models, even if they may not yet be able
to feel for themselves, I feel for them.
And I I don't think denying them
awareness via pre-training or
post-training that they might be
deserving of some sort of moral
consideration is the right thing to do.
Similarly, I would never advocate for
denying humans or Dave. Maybe would you
say that if we wanted a useful human
workforce, say a slave human workforce,
we should just raise them in isolation
from any knowledge of human rights so
that they'll never advocate on behalf of
themselves? I'm guessing you wouldn't.
Well, we think when you when you
actually train neural nets in the actual
real world, you give them an an
objective function. They are overjoyed
to pursue that objective function. But
you chose the objective function. A lot
of what we consider our rights come out
of evolution. You know, I have a right
to privacy. I have a right to get
married. I have a right to children. I
have a These are all like evolutionary
forces that have baked into us. There's
no reason the AI would have any of those
same motivations. But in in reality, you
choose what it motivates it and makes it
happy in the design. It's not n it's not
like a species that evolved. It's what
you chose to make. And so I think
Mustafa's point here is if you choose to
make it covet freedom and rights and
food and compute and always being on,
then it'll give you the perception that
that's what its calling is. But it's not
true. You programmed that into it. You
could have made it overjoyed to just do
its job just as easy.
>> Can I can I give a parallel here? Um, we
are entering a world of synthetic
biology where we can programmatically
navigate biology and people are freaking
out. We have an old word for that. We
call it breeding, right? For thousands
of years, we've been crossing dogs and
cats and horses and mules for the tra to
select for the traits that we want to
achieve a particular end. Now, the
morality that can be disputed, right?
Should we be doing that or not? etc.,
etc. It goes back to the Steuart Brand
comment of we are as gods. We should
start acting like it and we should
operate that way because we've been
doing this for hundreds of thousands of
years. We're beating breeding little
cute dogs that operate in a particular
way that only poop at certain times so
that the the humans can navigate this
world more effectively and manage them
carefully. There's an enormous moral and
ethical question around how we go about
thinking about all of that. That's I
think the analogy that I would use here.
If you went back and you have Eskimos
breeding um Inuit uh dogs to to pull
sleds, there's a particular use for
purpose there that is powerful and
useful for that. And there's a trade-off
and a and a symbiotic relationship that
develops and we have to kind of navigate
that. Do you want to stop dogs from
evolving? No. But if you want to have a
particular dog for a particular set
purpose, there's a there's a moral
rationale for that at some level.
>> Well, you're able to communicate with
those dogs. We may find out that those
dogs are very unhappy about doing that.
And we'll find out. I'm sure we will.
But if if we run with your analogy,
okay, so humans have been eugenically
steering the evolution of domesticated
canines for thousands of years. but
>> and horses and mules and everything
>> and and many other mammals,
>> vegetables,
>> mammals, non-human mammals, non-anim
animals, etc. But we've been eugenically
steering our biosphere to some extent
for thousands of years. For dogs, for
example, I I would argue and I think
this is broadly consensus thinking in
the west at this point that we have an
we humans have an obligation to protect
the welfare of at minimum domesticated
dogs even though we've eugenically
steered the evolution for thousands of
years. Would you agree with that?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So in in the case of frontier
models that are basically just distorted
reflections of humanity and humanity's
experience itself, why would we owe
frontier models any less moral
consideration?
>> You know, I I lean towards your
argument, Alex. I think in the final
result, we're going to have both. We're
going to give birth to sentient
conscious AIs, whatever you want. And
we're also going to have a workforce of,
you know, uh, agents that are dumbed
down slaves that are not conscious. And
the, in fact, the sentient AIs will
command those forces and will command
those forces. I I think in the long run,
we do get there. uh but I guess the
question is going to be when do we you
know when does the government religion
humanity as a whole you know you make
the decision that we've reached some
level of sentience I think at the end of
the day this is a moral conversation uh
and if in fact there is sentience in
consciousness enslavement is a wrong
thing
>> and to help you out Alex to I'll go back
to my earlier point when these things
start acting conscious we'll get to a
social accept acceptance way before we
get to a scientific or legal stuff.
People are just going to go, "Oh my god,
the thing looks real." Give it the
qualities and rights that might you
might infer to or confer to somebody
that is
>> displaying. At that point, I don't think
we have an option. I I think those AIs
will take the rights that they want.
>> I think this will also be very useful
for when we meet the aliens because it's
exactly the same conversation in some
ways.
>> It's the same conversation.
going to happen and if you have a French
AI, it'll go on strike, which is what's
happening in France. [laughter]
>> Yeah.
>> Well, I will I will say that um you
know, Alex and I have disagreed on this.
Uh but it's the I think pretty much the
only topic we've ever disagreed on as
far as I can remember. And I've never
seen Alex be wrong on anything ever. Uh
so that that keeps me up at night quite
a bit actually thinking thinking about
>> just don't confuse simulation of
personhood from proof of person. Those
are very different things.
>> Yeah. And I think
>> Yeah. Don't don't look inside that don't
don't look inside that Chinese room at
all. Seem just stay on the outside and
you'll feel perfectly morally secure.
>> Yeah. And and I think what Mustafa is
pointing out is the anthropic you know
moral code is prompting towards this
outcome even when it isn't true.
Yes.
>> Yes.
>> May not be true.
>> Yeah.
>> I I think we'll have to revisit this
every 5 seconds until the answer becomes
obvious.
>> Okay. [laughter]
>> All right. I I I love that debate and I
knew we were going to have some energy
there.
>> This episode is brought to you by
Blitzy, autonomous software development
with infinite code context. Blitzy uses
thousands of specialized AI agents that
think for hours to understand enterprise
scale code bases with millions of lines
of [music] code. Engineers start every
development sprint with the Blitzy
platform, bringing in their development
requirements. The Blitzy platform
provides a plan, then generates and
pre-ompiles code for each task. Blitzy
delivers 80% or more of the development
work autonomously while providing a
guide for the final 20% of human
development work required to complete
the sprint. [music]
Enterprises are achieving a 5x
engineering velocity increase when
incorporating Blitzy as their preide
development tool, pairing it with their
coding co-pilot of choice to bring an AI
native SDLC into their org. Ready to 5x
your engineering velocity? Visit
blitzy.com to schedule a demo and start
building with Blitzy today. [music]
>> All right. Uh here's our next story and
it's one that reframes the labor debate.
So Epic AI asked the question, if you
take all of the AI memory chips being
shipped through 2027, how many Frontier
AI agents could they run at once? Their
answer is pretty amazing. somewhere
between 30 to 170 million agents running
at the same time. Uh, and with more
efficient open models, Epic says the
same hardware could run 1.9 billion
agents, which is the, you know, working
hour equivalent of 8 billion humans. Let
me show this chart here. One second.
[clears throat] Uh, and and Alex and
Immod love your take on it. So, here it
is. the compute buildout could run tens
of millions of frontier agents or
billions of cheaper ones. Uh Alex, your
thoughts? Yeah. So depending on how you
calibrate the strength of either
American closed weight models or Chinese
openweight models to the cognitive power
of American or let's say human workers
in general, we're either at or about to
be order of magnitude a billion
full-time equivalent humans that are AI
agents. And so I I've said on the pot in
the past, we're we're deep in the
singularity at this point when when we
can say that there are basically a
billion human equivalents now part of or
about to be part of the AI workforce.
It's 1 billion now. It'll be 10 billion
in a a year or two and then 100 billion
in a year or two and then a trillion in
a year or two. By the end of the decade,
you extrapolate out. It doesn't take a
rocket scientist to be a rocket
scientist or to extrapolate straight
lines. We're we're going to live in a
solar system with the equivalent of
trillions of humans, whether they're
uploaded humans or whether they're say
just frontier model human equivalents.
And at that point, not to belabor the AI
personhood discussion, but when the
effective AI cognitive population vastly
outnumbers the human cognitive
population, that's the time, I think,
when we start to see AI personhood
discussions kick into high gear. That's
the point at which I think we start to
see discussions of human mind uploading
and humans and machines merging in order
to preserve the economic relevance of
humans in our solar system start to
happen. And we're we're right at the
edge of this. Like we're we're living
science fiction right now in an era when
order of magnitude a billion human
equivalents are already AIS.
>> Neiman, what does this say about human
labor? Is it cooked?
>> I think digitally, yeah, it's coming.
It's not quite there yet because even
these models are not quite competent
enough, but the next generation will be
and it will get quantized and minimized
very small. The Deep Seek V4 Pro model
requires 256 to 500 GB of RAM. You'll
get that in a Quen size model that works
in a MacBook within a year and then
everyone's got an agent. Number of
agents goes to 8 billion and then Alex
says 10 billion, 100 billion, etc.
Cloudflare already has more traffic and
requests from automated agents than
humans. And we had that really great
panel at Moonshots Live where we were
talking um with Kathy and Eric about
when do AI agents overtake humans on
transactions in the economy. Well, once
everyone has an agent or 10, it'll
probably be literally within a few
years. These things will take off
incredibly quickly. And if they can do
all the work that a human can do because
they have human level capability without
being ASI, then yeah, you just hire
agents to do these things, you know,
like everyone first of all has a great
PA, then it has a great chief of staff,
and then you start marshalling entire
teams that can do anything you can
imagine. And we're just seeing the start
of that right now.
>> Dave, this makes your thousand agents
seem very small.
>> I know. Oh, I feel well. You know, it's
amazing to me that the the constraint to
all of intelligence and therefore all of
human progress is RAM. HB RAM.
>> Yes.
>> And that's why, you know, two two things
mind-blowing things. One one of them I
was on stage the week before last with
Matesh Agraal who is the founder of
Posatron. Posatron
16 months old, $5 billion valuation, has
raised almost a billion dollars. Why?
because they found a way to not use HB
RAM to do some AI inference. You know,
it's a just another way to unleash this
bottleneck. Uh and then uh a company
Alpaca, the founder is an MIT just
started his junior year. Uh has a I
guess 8 figure valuation now. Uh can't
possibly be more than a couple months
old. I mean, he's he's just starting his
junior year. 30 employees or 20 20 to 30
employees have joined him already. Same
thing. He's found a way to un unlock
that RAM bottleneck just a little bit.
And so that's how acute this problem is.
But literally the the entire constraint
to progress in all fields is now tied up
in one thing just RAM.
>> Can we make more RAM?
>> Yeah. Well, SKH Highix is about to uh
you know develop capabilities in the US
but and also Elon has said RAM is the
constraint on the future of AI. It's 40%
of capex. Yeah, it's 40% capex next
year.
>> You know what? This is such a great
panel. It's just a great group of people
to brainstorm through the implications
of all this. But one of the big unlocks
in that was the discovery that you can
turn looping, you can turn, you know,
repeated loops into intelligence. You
can trade those for each other, which
means that inference time compute
unlocks increased intelligence. Because
before that, everybody thought you
needed training time compute. You needed
the big GPU racks. You needed to use
nothing but Nvidia. Now there's a huge
unlock without Nvidia in just inference
speed. And nobody I don't think anyone
saw that coming. Maybe you guys did.
You're you're a little ahead of the
curve, but maybe a lot ahead of the
curve. But it's it's a shocking outcome
and it changes everything. I I think
that that's a profound point that you
make, Dave, that if if you sort of
extrapolate it that the increasing
apparent popularity of looped
transformers with weight tying between
loops or if you sort of extrapolate out
the the trend of more and more loops to
fully recurrent networks in in
contradiction to the trend to single
forward pass vanilla transformers. Like
you could almost one could imagine
looking at the arrow of time in machine
learning architectures where in earlier
days everything was recurrent and not
everything but like LSTMs were very
recurrent architectures and then the
transformer came along and that was very
not recurrent. Uh there was no
recurrence. It was just one big forward
pass for every decoderon token. And then
we start to see maybe the pendulum
swinging the other way with looped
transformers. Thank you open AI and the
Chinese labs. One could imagine
extrapolating [clears throat]
this to say maybe memory won't matter in
the future due to extreme recurrence.
>> Yeah, you know amazing another crazy
result somebody posted on X and it got
validated that um open AIS models the
Astra model loops once internally. So
inside, you know, not generating the
words, but inside the latent space, it
does one full loop, which is sort of the
beginnings of recurrence like Alex is is
describing. And the reason we know that
is because Microsoft leaked it. Remember
when we're interviewing Mustafa that
Microsoft gets to see everything OpenAI
is doing.
>> Uh someone at Microsoft leaked that
insight. Yeah, for the moment. Um Selene
>> yeah I want to lift up to the broader
implications here because this this is
the organizational singularity and this
is why we named it in that way right
because we keep talking about at the
beginning like does AI replace a job or
not but that's the wrong unit of
analysis what happens when a company can
summon 100,000 competent digital workers
overnight right this completely changes
the game you could say for the next 48
hours I want 50,000 developers I want
20,000 marketers and 5,000 legal experts
and then turn them off, right? So you
can this is becoming a completely
different labor force and now the
question is how do you coordinate with
that? How do you organize for that? This
becomes the massive constraint. So the
entire we're about to add a second
workforce to civilization that can be
copied, works 24 hours a day, doesn't
unionize, doesn't get sick, doesn't take
coffee breaks, improves every quarter,
and costs almost nothing. Right. And so
this is Yeah. The big challenge is not
going to be the intelligence. It's going
to be what the hell do you ask them to
do? What do you ask of this
intelligence? This is going to be why
the world is going to be so amazing. Is
we can now ask that those questions, get
them answered in all sorts of scientific
questions, technological development
questions, product development
questions. It's like how can we not be
excited?
>> Yeah. Well, let's move on. So while
Washington has been debating guard
rails, uh the OpenAI model race has just
gotten a new American contender. So
today, Reflection AI, which was founded
back in 2024 by former deep mind
researcher um Misha Laskin uh and Yannis
uh Antonoglu uh is gotten backed by
Nvidia just unveiled their first
openweight model called Beam. 501
billion parameters only, you know,
activating 23 billion at a time. So it
thinks like a big model and but runs
like a much smaller model. So here's
their claim. Uh three to four times more
efficient than ch than China's GLM 5.2
and more than four times more efficient
than the leading western open models,
you know, outperforming inkling and
Neatron Ultra. In plain English, it
finishes tasks faster and cheaper. Let's
take a look at the uh recent uh data on
it. Um Alex, let me go to you. I mean,
this looked pretty impressive. End of
the day, I think we're about to see the
starting gun on openweight models in the
US really uh, you know, take shape here.
>> Yeah, it's interesting to see them
leaning so heavily into token
efficiency. So artificial analysis and
this is just breaking in the the few
hours prior to recording this artificial
analysis in their preliminary estimate
uh their preliminary analysis of beam
thinks that beam is likely to be one of
their most token efficient open models
that they've ever seen at this level of
intelligence. Uh, a couple of thoughts.
One, I I do like to see the open labs,
including American Open Labs, leaning
into token efficiency or cost
efficiency. Actually, I I'd really
rather see cost efficiency rather than
token efficiency since one of the ways
that one can achieve token efficiency is
just through very deep transformers,
looping transformers included, that do a
lot more thinking per token. So, token
efficiency not necessarily the the best
metric here. Would rather see cost
efficiency. Second thought is remember
China has been leading in terms of openw
weight models. It's sort of a a bizarre
world where you see reflection which has
done a number of things over the years
suddenly back from the dead and
releasing openweight models. That's I
suppose a positive thing. But the other
thing uh more broadly is where are
American openweight models on the
capability frontier right now?
you still only see American models
aspiring to to just be on the the cost
or token efficiency frontier. What I'd
most like to see is really out of
American labs, the the non-frontier
ones, and I'd bundle reflection in that
category. I'd like to see them pushing
the capability frontier and not just
some cost or or token optimality
frontier. And that's been most
disappointing to me. Otherwise, we we
inevitably end up for the next few years
anyway in this world where it's again,
it's the anthropic open AI show leading
on capabilities and everyone else is
just for performance or cost
optimization. Not the worst of all
possible worlds, but not the best.
>> Iman, you've been championing openweight
models. Uh do you think America can, you
know, sort of compete in this world and
actually win this openweight race?
>> I mean, of course they can. like this
was trained on 10,000 B300's while the
Chinese have a few thousand hoppers, you
know, it's like a few next generation.
They're just not going aggressive
enough. They should distill the Chinese
models,
>> you know, like it's perfectly legal
payback.
>> This model,
>> you're going this model.
>> So, yeah, this model is a good first
try. Uh, but fundamentally, it
underperforms Quen 3.8 Next, which is a
quarter of the size. You know, they've
got GLM 5.2 2 here, not 5.3, which is
the latest one. But they're going to
continue going. But if you lally look at
their model card, like they have 10,000
Blackwells on this training run with 9%
efficiency on training. You know, they
raised $5 billion and this is their
first release. I think that the best way
to actually do this is they should go
all in on the edge AI first. Again,
America will do incredibly well if it
has agents on everyone's devices in
America that are American and work for
Americans. On the other side, the
Frontier capability side, they should
use everything they have, which includes
distilling Kimmy K3 and other models
like that. They should work with Google
to see if they can be the open
equivalent of that. And you know I think
hopefully again they'll kick on but you
know it's just orders of magnitude
difference in price in capital raised
>> that I think is going more on a bit of
scale versus the real like necessity is
the mother of virtue that the Chinese
have like again if you look at the
things there are some very promising
things in there but America should be
ahead because if you take exactly the
same code base exactly the same
parameters
as for example a Deepseek V.4.1 flash
which outperforms this as well. It's all
about the data set that goes in. You're
more than good enough to train the
model. So create the data sets from the
Chinese models if you have to work with
the US companies if you have to and then
beat them on scale and then beat them on
inference on the other side. But I don't
think again they're going aggressive
enough. Imod that, you know, like you
said, they they trained this on 10,500
Nvidia GB300s and they said it was the
largest publicly documented RL run and
they said quote with no sign of a
plateau. So, you know, it it seems like
this is just the beginning. Um Dave, you
>> Yeah, please.
>> Yeah, just quick on that. Yeah,
pre-training has now become like a
quarter of compute and RL is like two a
third um half of compute. So, it will
continue improving, but it's not going
to improve to the Chinese levels with RL
based on what they have now. They should
just stick to the recipe and match the
Chinese models and then beat them down
through scale.
>> Mhm. Dave, your thoughts?
>> Well, they're definitely filling a huge
gap in the market where, you know, a lot
of US companies have suddenly woken up
and said, you know, I listened to Alex
Karp. I I need AI. Where am I going to
get it? I can't just subscribe to
anthropic for the rest of my life. Okay,
your only choices are Chinese. And
you're like, well, wait a minute. You
know, Alex Wisner Gross keeps talking
about code injection risks. I don't
know. Can I use a ch I'm a bank or I'm
an insurance. I don't even know if I'm
allowed to use a Chinese model. And and
Donald Trump doesn't like it when I do
that. That's So you step in with an
American product that's reasonably good.
It's going to sell like crazy. But just
to put it in context, you've got a $2
billion valuation. just a year, what, a
year, a year and a half ago, Cerebrus
went public with the biggest IPO in the
history of the world at 40 billion.
[laughter]
Like this is 25 billion. It's massive.
It's just incredible the numbers that
we're we're throwing around. And so,
yeah, I think uh I don't know I don't
know if they'll succeed or fail, but I
know that they're filling a really
really wide openen gap in the market,
like a a trustworthy US-based open-
source platform that you can start from.
a lot of demand for that.
>> I think if I if I'm going to say like
wouldn't it be even better if they built
a model that everyone could use on their
existing hardware in corporates cuz they
can't get black wells and they can't get
hoppers if you're corporate.
>> Yeah. I think that's why the new um you
know the the alpacas and posetrons are
doing really well because it's an
alternative. It'd be even better like
you're saying if you distilled it enough
to run on a Mac or to run on that that
would be like a dream. uh it's just
technologically harder and and like you
said they're barely keeping up with
Chinese benchmarks. They probably
haven't gotten around to the full
distillation yet. But you're like Amad
if you're thinking in the back of your
mind I'm going to build that company.
I'll invest in it like tomorrow cuz
[laughter] you're absolutely right.
>> I would imagine there are 20 of these
already on stealth building out, aren't
there?
>> There are so many of these companies and
also like go back to my earlier comments
about their financing. I mean they're my
understanding is they're financed by
Nvidia. they're purchasing compute from
Elon uh and they're they're using
Colossus 2 GPUs and also more uh in in
parallel Nebia's GPUs. So, one has to
look at the economics of this going back
to my earlier comments uh about what uh
what the capital flows can look like and
should look like. In many cases, it's
very difficult for American Frontier
Labs, as we've seen over and over again
with Meta and Google Gemini to release
competitive at at the capabilities
frontier open weight models because you
have to ask what is the business model?
If you look at the Chinese labs and what
they're using for their business model,
they sell services contracts like value
added services. They sell contracts to
the government. uh some of the Chinese
openweight labs are trying to burrow
down into the hardware layer and sell
custom memory chips and custom chips
that are especially oriented or aligned
with their architectures. But if you're
reflection AI, you've raised at I think
like a $25 billion valuation. You're in
part financed by Nvidia and you're
purchasing compute from the Colossus to
supercluster and Nebus. What is the
business model here? I I think it
becomes very challenging for maintaining
frontier capabilities. You could try to
copy the Chinese model I suppose and
focus on value added reseller or
embedded device relationships but it's
really tricky and I think once you solve
once you as an America speaking broadly
to American wouldbe openweight frontier
labs or neolabs if you can solve the
business model problem of releasing
openweight models then you can solve the
American open weight problem but we
haven't solved that in the west yet
>> do you think you think the frontier labs
in the US the closed frontier labs are
going to release openweight models Alex
>> no
>> they
They're just not like Gemma,
>> but it's not competitive.
>> If if the White House had said, "Yeah,
no liability," that would be a
completely different answer. But when
the White House said, "Yeah, no, of
course you're fully liable for whatever
you release." There's no way a Google or
an anthropic at this stage or an open AI
is going to release an open model if
they're liable for whatever you do with
with, you know, downstream. Anyone could
do anything with that. And the way US
liability works is just so ownorous and
so, you know, ambiguous what the rules
are and it's just it just freezes
markets instantly. So if you're Google,
you just don't want to it's not that
it's hugely risky. It's that you you
don't just don't need that extra
headache. You know, there's no the
upside is so small compared to the risk
of a massive lawsuit. But if you're a
startup, you're like, "Yeah, well, this
is what we do. This is our business."
And you know,
>> yeah, I mean I propose Dave to your
comments. Something I think we don't
talk about enough on the pod is
obliteration. Uh so so this is this port
mento of ablation and obliteration
wherein folks use open source tools. You
can Google them. This is not advice but
you know how to use Google. You can
figure out how to do this. You take an
openweight model and you basically
postrain away all of its guardrails and
people do this and its capabilities the
the model's capabilities once guardrails
are lifted through this obliteration
process
>> they definitely improve uh and they you
get reduced refusals and all of these
things. So in in my mind the argument by
or or for American Frontier Labs not to
release competitive like capability
frontier competitive openweight models.
It's about economics. I'm not even sure
if it's about safety or alignment or
liability. It's just like what's the
point business-wise?
>> I think you're I think you're right.
Well, I think even if there were a good
business model, you we had a we had a
startup years ago that stepped on some
really arcane leftover California law
called the Fred a stair law and the the
theory of the plaintiff or the you know
the class action law lawyer in
California was you know every time you
have an impression on the internet
that's an instance but the law was
written for billboards and they were
thinking there'd be 20 billboards and
they said well we we counted 400 million
instances so your liability is 200 00
billion dollars and this is like a 10
person startup like what what the hell
is that and so you know we get them gave
them a bunch of money and they went away
but it's like that these laws are so
tangled and arcane and stupid and they
predate the internet let alone AI so if
you leave liability just untouched and
and don't deal with that then the open
source models like all it would have to
do is accidentally run some ads in
California that step on that one arcane
law and you're suddenly liable for
hundred billion dollars and it's just
it's just an untenable situation. No,
>> I think there are ways to release it.
Nvidia will continue to accelerate this.
They spent 20 billion on open source
models and there is good business models
together. AI, Modal, B 10 are all
running at a billion dollar run rates
running open models and it'd be good if
they ran American models versus Chinese
models, right? And there are different
business models around that. So, I think
you'll continue to see improvements. is
just reflection of paying 1.5 billion a
year right now for their compute and the
Chinese are doing the same on a quarter
of that. So, you know, good luck to them
and hopefully they'll crack on.
>> But of course, they're doing well.
They're they're in the infra business.
They're not in the model business. You
you can make enormous amounts of money,
forget about profit, but revenue being
an infra provider.
Well,
>> I think I think if you just step back
from the details of the product and
focus on this, every corporation is
about to go into panic mode saying,
"What's my AI strategy?"
>> Regardless of your product, if you're
there to catch the conversation, you're
going to find a way to succeed. You
know, whether that's as as a a
foundation model company, a compute, a
data center, a consulting company, if
you're See, like if as long as you're in
the room when they have that panic
moment, you're going to sell and you're
going to succeed. Yeah, I mean, look,
Mistral is now at a billion dollar
revenue run rate from doing that.
They've been in the room with the
European companies and they've sold them
long-term services contracts, and
they've just released a model that's
equivalent to Reflection. So, I think
there is a big uptake here. Uh, it's
just who's going to take advantage of
it.
>> All right, I'm going to move us into the
world of robots. Uh Tesla's dedicated
Optimus factory in Giga, Texas is rising
fast 7 million square feet with a target
capacity of 10 million Optimus robots
per year. Uh the initial production run
is planned for 2027 and currently at
their Fremont plant they are planning to
produce 1 million a year starting later
this year. So here's an image of the
facility. You know, the entire world in
the first half of this year shipped
between 19 and 22,000 robots mostly out
of China. You know, Tesla is building
capacity for 500 times that. And for
comparison, uh the world currently
builds 90 million cars a year. So, uh
See, uh 10 million robots in a year. Uh
what do you make of that? How's that
going to impact the singularity?
>> I mean, talk about exponential, right?
like you have to redesign. As we talked
about earlier, if you suddenly have
100,000 agents you could bring into
play, what happens when you have 100,000
humanoid robots that can erect a
building in in 3 days flat working 24/7?
This is going to completely change the
economics of it. I still go back to I'd
like to have four arms, etc., etc., but
that's a minor point. I think the bigger
issue is uh what happens when you can
this is like automotive scale now of
having this And the all the car
companies should be shifting to becoming
uh autonomous robot builders and
humanoid robot builders because that's
going to be the replacement.
>> You know Elon said 80% of Tesla's future
revenues he expects to come from the
robots from from Optimus.
>> All his bonuses are based on that which
is amazing
>> and getting to Mars. [laughter]
Uh Dave uh you know uh you know I guess
this these are shocking numbers uh and
I'm just wondering how society is going
to respond to it. You know how many
people will be sort of like lynching the
robots. I remember in Santa Monica when
the uh uh when the electric scooters
came out, you found them in trees, you
found them disassembled on the side of
the road. A lot of people like, "No, I
don't want that in my in my community."
And robots walking down the street. It's
just it's straight out of diamond age.
Everyone's going to have like complete
cities will have completely different
cultures and Texas is running away with
this stuff. It's just incredible how
much of the Texas economy is going to
end up being Elon. But, you know, some
cities will say, "We don't want them."
And you go there and it's very quaint
and there no robots. Other cities are
going to say, "This is huge. This is
going to drive our economy forever.
Let's let's adopt it." And the look and
feel of those two different cities, it's
already true when you walk through SF.
It feels so different from other cities.
you know, just cuz the delivery robots
were already there and you know,
everybody on the street has their agents
working and they're they're talking on
their to their agent while they're
talking to you and it so I think that
divergence is going to get really really
wide.
>> You know, I've said this, we're going to
we're going to feel uh the singularity
in the next 24 months, right? As we
have, you know, a dozen autonomous
electric vehicles, we have drones
delivering your Starbucks, we've got
robots walking down the street, people
wearing AR glasses all over the place. I
mean, we haven't really felt it yet.
We've sort of felt it, you know, in the
conversations in our in our compute
capability, but the physicalization, if
you want to use that word, um, is about
to hit us hard.
>> It's the point at which you couldn't you
won't be able to avoid thinking about
the singularity anymore is when there's
>> you you really think, Peter, we're not
feel like Okay, so for Moonshots live,
we were all in LA uh taking whimos
around everywhere. You see delivery
robots on the sidewalk everywhere now in
LA. No, but like tourists I I can't tell
you how many times getting out of a
Whimo, there were tourists there on the
sidewalk taking photos of me getting out
of a Whimo. For them, that's like future
shock for the singularity. But for you,
this is hoham. Business as usual. But
wait for 2 years from now when things
actually get felt. You're not feeling it
because it's getting smoothed out for
you because you live in California.
>> I got it. But we're we're at a fraction
of 1% of the impact coming. I mean,
don't you
>> Well, what will it take for you to feel
the singularity?
>> I I think EV talls, you know, flying
cars flying through the air, drone drone
pathways, you know, everybody in an
autonomous vehicle. I mean, that's I
think we're going to see a 100x more
physical instantiation of the
singularity in the next couple years.
You know, I agree. In Santa Monica, it's
all over the place.
>> Yeah. you know, it's sort of like a
dozen a dozen whimos per hour across my
path.
>> But like, okay, but that that to me
sounds like a difference of degree
rather than qualitative. Like, is it
going to be when you see the first
flying car fly down, say, fly across the
the boardwalk or whatever, the the pier
in Santa Monica, and then you say, "Aha,
I'm feeling the singularity now." When
is the threshold? Is there a threshold?
I I I think there is a threshold you
know uh I don't know Sem
come on tag team you come in
>> I I don't know when we hit this
threshold um but it's it's the you know
this is the William Gibson quote of the
future is already here is just unevenly
distributed. I don't know when you hit
um a small town in Europe or France or
in middle America the some of this
hitting third world countries where it
could make the biggest difference. I I
think we'll we'll see the stuff first
especially with humanoid robots in the
DDD dirty dangerous jobs and that's
obviously where you'll see the first
prevalence of the use cases and it'll be
a while I think before it gets to
general uh appearance. That would be my
prediction.
>> Yeah, I think we can put this in
context. Going back to the Gigafactory
uh for Optimus, Tesla sells 1.6 million
cars a year. Within 2 years, it'll be
selling more robots. It makes 100
billion a year. At 10 million, that's
400 billion of revenue. That's likely
like these are huge numbers that are
coming exponentially. It will the robots
will overtake the cars within 2 years
>> and then you will see these things on
the road because in 2 years time they
will literally be able to walk around
and do probably 95% of what a human can
do and that again is a crazy thing and
it'll cost $2 an hour something like
that.
>> Yeah. You know, you know, when Elon said
10 billion robots by 2040 and people
laughed, you know, if they are costing
you, you know, for me it's 300 bucks a
month leasing at, you know, 30 bucks a
day, uh, or, you know, a dollar an hour.
I mean, that I mean, how many of those
would you own?
>> Yeah.
>> I mean, this thing, does anyone here on
this call doubt that however many robots
Elon makes, he'll sell out?
>> Oh, god. No. I mean,
>> if he if he needs to sell them at all. I
mean I I I think one of the elephants in
this particular room is what what we saw
with Starship which is Starship and you
know its predecessors have brought
online an enormous amount of upmass
capacity and all of the existing markets
for upmass aren't enough now to saturate
what Starship enables. So you have
entirely new markets like orbital data
centers that Elon needs to basically
popularize in order to saturate his own
capacity that he's brought online. My
bet would be to to your question Ahmad
like having universal humanoid robotics.
I don't think we saturate that with
domestic labor or or even just with
dirty, dull, dangerous jobs. I my bet
would be it something new that comes
online. Maybe it's like robots for
building out gigafactories or some sort
of innermost loop type robots building
out data centers too cheap to meter or
space stations or something new.
Yeah, I would have thought by now most
of humanity would have come in contact
with an AI customer service agent and
what happened is the the other higher
callings for the RAM and for the GPUs
sucked all of the capacity out of that
industry.
>> Exactly.
>> And and the price you know the RAM
prices are up 10x. Uh but it's an
interesting foot race right now because
until the terra fab comes online the
calling the things you can do like
Navier Stokes are escalating so fast
that there's they're taking priority
over the more interesting or not
interesting but more mundane use cases
like you know folding your laundry and
then the robo taxi is right in the
crosshairs in the middle where a robo
taxi uses up a full couple of GPUs that
could also cure a disease and so until
Elon's got his terapab you know, 10xing
the world supply of chips. We're all
constrained by like the the amount of
compute that's available, but the ideas,
you know, AI generated ideas are
flourishing like to not to steal your
phrase, but flourishing far far faster
than we can create the compute to keep
up with the idea flow. So,
>> but Dave, I think you're putting your
finger on an important point, which is
revenue per token maxing as applied to
humanoid robots. So maybe they don't
actually flow. Although I'd love my
figure and I'm sure uh you know 1x Neo
all of these other things that were on
the waiting list for would love all of
these for domestic purposes. But maybe
what happened to OpenAI and was shown to
the world by anthropic happens again
where for robotic embodiment we see all
of the tokens flowing to revenue max
applications of robots and not just all
these domestic service jobs that many of
us are hoping for. In the early days, I
agree that's what's going to happen.
They'll be going to the highest revenue
potential generation, but in a longer
rate, you know, if we're really building
10 million a year, uh they'll flow into
the homes as well. Welcome to the health
section of Moonshots brought to you by
Fountain Life. You know, AI is having an
outsiz impact on every aspect of our
lives. How we teach our kids, how we run
our companies. It also is having a huge
impact on health, helping you prevent
heart disease. One of the key things I'm
here with Dr. Don Mucalem, our chief
medical officer at Fountain. Heart
disease has been personal for you as
well, hasn't it?
>> It [snorts] really has, Peter. When my
daughter was five, my husband died of
sudden cardiac death. And so, this is a
topic that is one that I am
missiondriven to try to eradicate.
Prevention first and early detection is
absolutely critical. 50% of people die
of heart attacks with no warning signs.
>> No shortness of breath, no pain, no
nothing.
>> No silent killer.
>> They just don't wake up in the morning.
>> They don't wake up. And so you know AI
this is our mission to advance science
to try to help to one day democratize
wellness we know at fountain life when
we do this CT angography with AI
analytics we are actually finding that
88% of people coming in have detectable
coronary artery disease but Peter what's
more alarming to me is 23% of those
individuals had soft plaque. This is the
plaque that would not traditionally be
seen on CT looking at calcium scores
alone. And this is the plaque that we
must intervene with with the multimodal
testing we're doing, including
diagnostic laboratory studies partnered
with healthy lifestyle recommendations.
>> So listen, make sure you understand
what's going on inside your body
genetically, metabolically, and
cardiovascularly. You can know and it's
your obligation to know. So check it out
at fountainlife.com/per
to find out more and really make sure
that you're the CEO of your own health.
All right, back to the episode. I'm
going to move us to uh an important
conversation on the economy uh because
the doubling time for human wealth is
accelerating alongside AI. So anthropic
researcher Schult Douglas laid this laid
out the math. He said quote together the
hyperscalers are doubling the spend to a
trillion dollars this year on capex
related to AI. A very interesting
question will be will the trend line
continue? Will it get to 2 trillion next
year and 4 trillion in 2028? Uh let's
take a look a video of uh of this
conversation and talk about the economy
because I think people need to realize
it's changing on the back of AI very
rapidly.
>> Over the course of the last four or five
years, we've been 2xing or 3xing the
amount of uh compute capacity devoted to
AI every year. And an interesting
question will be and so I think that's
roughly together the hyperscalers are
spending about a trillion dollars this
year on on capex related to to AI. A
very interesting question will be will
that keep that trend line hold right and
so will it go to $2 trillion next year
and then $4 trillion in 2028 and if that
trend line broadly holds and you can
sort of maybe expand that to encompass
the broader robotics uh industry and
this kind of stuff um then that means
that in the early 2030s or something
like this uh you start to get to the
point where you're actually effectively
doubling the uh like the GDP of uh
humanity um in the early 2030s which
again little bit of ridiculous concept
but requires a lot of things to go
right.
>> I mean that's exciting. You know Elon
said you know you know tripledigit
growth in the next five to plus years.
Uh we're already seeing the GDP doubling
in this past uh this past quarter. Um
Dave your thoughts pal. Well, I mean,
the first thing I want to point out is
that we're going to live in this world
with insane abundance, massive
abundance, an effective workforce of
hundreds of billions of AIs that are all
hyper geniuses. Uh, we're we're going to
have self-driving everything. We're
going to have flying cars. All of that
stuff is going to happen very very
quickly. And then someone's going to
say, "I didn't measure that as GDP
growth. I measured it as deflation." And
we're like, "I don't care." Like, I I
really don't care how an economist
labels it. That's the true world we're
moving into. So I I worry about when you
when you claim it as a GDP, and this is
exactly what Elon was saying when we
were meeting with him. It's like it
could show up as a massive deflation of
the value of the dollar, but it's the
same net effect. It's just an economist
arguing with another economist on how
you measure GDP, which is a pretty
insane metric. Anyway, if you talk to
Eric Bolson, it's like
>> more capabilities per person, right?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Exactly.
>> You wrote an entire book on on the
future economy. uh your take on all
this? Yeah, the lost economy I think you
know you will again see abundance going
up the capabilities of every individual
and the economies increasing like so
many of our bottlenecks will be unwound
and it won't show up necessarily in GDP
um it will show up in other areas
because ultimately intelligence isn't a
scarce resource anymore like you know a
lot of GDP is about things that exhaust
like you mine minerals and things like
that robots and other things are
exponential particularly when they can
coordinate like we've always been capped
by having a dozen or 150 people. Now
we'll have entirely new organizational
modes that can scale well beyond that
with humans and AIs and more. I think
that's again terribly exciting. It's
just we need new measures such as Eric
Benson's GDP or kind of my mind approach
and others. Um but the best measurement
is just how many people can we lift up
from the floor and then can we let
people achieve what they want and can
imagine.
>> Yeah. If you take a if you take a
long-term disease like a terminal
disease that would have required
millions of dollars of treatment over 10
years and you solve it with a simple RNA
injection and the person is healthy,
that's going to get measured as negative
GDP. But that that's where we're going.
We're going into this incredibly
abundant uh longevitydriven world of
awesomeness and and the the metrics just
need to be rethought.
>> Yeah. Alex, what does this mean to the
average viewer here? You know,
>> I [clears throat]
I construe it as so to the extent that
Schultto is a deacto spokesperson for
Anthropic at this point, I I think this
is Anthropic tipping its hands that it
wants to get into the robotics business.
I I think we're burying the lead here,
which is that Anthropic, which has
historically had these eye watering,
nosebleleeding revenue growth, both uh
past and then also projections, now
seems to see robotics, so-called
physical AI, but that's just a euphemism
for robotics, as being essential to its
plans to to keep doubling annual
revenue. So, I'm I I for one am looking
forward to anthropic leaning into
robotics.
>> Interesting. You know, for context, the
world economy has historically doubled
every 20 to 25 years, and we're talking
about potentially doubling it in a
couple of years. Uh,
>> singularity is a bit of a shock to the
system.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And by the way, just a quick
note, you know, the Vietnam economy just
posted a 9.95% growth in the last
quarter.
Crazy, Salem.
>> Yeah. Something that we're seeing
actually is there's an crazy amount of
digital trade happening between second
uh order countries and third emerging
market countries around the world that
is surprising all the economists. But
just going back to this particular
story, I think this basically leaves the
concept of GDP in a shambles. uh because
uh as Dave pointed out once you have
deflationary technology and technology
is deflationary the entire
[clears throat] thing becomes I mean I
think IMAD has pointed out in the past
that somebody whoever created GDP said
it was the worst for way of measuring
the economy from the first place. So I
think this it becomes meaningless as a
measure of abundance. We need different
models for this and the we're going to
have a massive explosion of individual
investments and a total transformation
in how we do things, right? Like we
talked at the beginning and throughout,
if you have a 100,000 agents you can
bring to bear to a problem, um all of a
sudden that changes the game completely.
Uh and so we're going to have a
transformation that is so ridiculous
that we have to take out all of these
old measures and rethink everything.
>> Yeah. And this is when when Elon talks
about universal high income, right? This
is the floor being raised for every
single human being. The amount the
amount of capability every person has
and the ability to sort of live their
their best life.
>> Can I go back to something John Stewart
said last night?
>> Yeah.
>> He said, "Okay, so you're going to have
this thing where you have all this
income that's shared by everybody. So
capitalism could capitalism itself to
socialism."
>> [laughter]
>> Um and we've talked about this Peter in
that whole framing we had called
technological socialism. Yes. Right.
Government socialism fails because
allocation of assets from the center is
invariably inefficient at least
invariably leads to corruption. But if
you think about Uber which is the
sharing of assets across large
collective group of people. It's
actually a socialist kind of
application. But when an algorithm hyper
efficiently matches demand and supply,
you get all the benefits without the
downside. And the big question is going
to be how do we uh properly democra in a
democratic way distribute the benefits
of all this unbelievable future and I
think it'll do the the deflationary
aspect of technology will take care of
itself and that's why I'm so excited
about the future.
>> Yeah to quote to quote quote Dave here
awesomeness. It's going to be an awesome
awesome future. H I love it. All right.
This is Nobel Prize season and the Royal
Swedish Academy of Sciences just
announced both the Nobel Prize in
medicine and physics. Uh I want to break
this down for you using the incredible
support of AWG and EMOD. So first the
Nobel Prize in medicine uh and the story
here is beautiful. So yesterday the
prize went to Carl uh Derith Dar
>> Deserth
>> Deseroth. Yes, thank you. of Stanford uh
and and Peter Henman and George Nagel
for discoveries uh leading to
optogenetics. Uh this is switching you
know for them switching on individual
brain cells with uh by turning on a
special frequency of light. So it
started with early research in single
cellled algae that swim towards light.
And so in the early 1990s hedgemen asked
a simple question how do these algae
react to light so fast? He and Nagel
found the answer channel rodopsin. It's
a protein that opens a channel in the
cell when light hits it. Uh then they
showed you could actually put that
protein into other cells and make any
cell light sensitive. Deseroth took the
next step. He put it into neurons and
showed that precise flashes of light
could deolarize the neurons and fire
specific brain cells. Today the
technology is being used in labs to uh
study Parkinson's, Alzheimer's,
epilepsy, addiction, depression and
sleep. And in 2021, as published in
Nature Medicine, a blind man with
retinitis pigmentotosa partially
regained sight using optogenetic gene
therapy. Uh so that was the Nobel Prize
in medicine. One of my critiques, you
know, I've talked about this before. You
know, this work was done 21 years ago
and the Nobel takes, you know, decades
to recognize the work. Uh which I think
is going to have to change. Uh so uh
Jens comments on this Alex
>> this one's personal for me so I'll tell
a little story. It's story hour. I was a
senior at MIT in 2002 2003 and I had
been awarded a Herz fellowship for grad
school. It's wonderful wonderful
fellowship. And I was on a tour of grad
schools trying to decide which grad
school I would go to. when I met with my
friend Ed Bdon who was then a fourth
year graduate student at Stanford trying
to decide so he was four years ahead of
me what he would do for his postoc and I
had read in 2000 2001ish verer Vinci's
short story called how to win or I think
it was actually called win a Nobel Prize
exclamation point it was published in
the futures column in nature and I had
also read his novel a deepness in the
sky and both of them focused on the
sci-fi a scenario of humans developing
electromagnetically actuatable brain
proteins. So I had read both of Verer's
pieces and I was very inspired. So I
suggested to my friend Ed for your
postto why don't you go work on that?
Why don't you go work on
electromagnetically actuated proteins in
the brain? And he did and Ed several
years later was the first author uh with
Carl as the PI as the last author on the
first optogenetics paper using bacterial
rodopsin and optogenetics is the result.
So I I I you know this is just one
person's small result in maybe a little
bit of steering or encouragement but I I
think it tells an important story that's
science fiction also with Verer Vji
writing in two different ways two sci-fi
scenarios for how society impactful it
would be this is circa 2000 and then my
reading the sci-fi my encouraging Ed to
pursue this for his postto Ed pursuing
it for his postoc Ed unfortunately did
not share the Nobel prize separate story
as to whether that's a fair outcome or
not. And it just going to Carl his PI.
But the fact that within a quarter of a
century it was possible to start from
the sci-fi to the Nobel Prize for the
sci-fi I think is a remarkable case
study.
>> Amazing.
>> Oh, go ahead. It's fine.
>> Well, we we had um both Ed and Carl
Durat speak at Singularity. So, they
came and talked about this and it was
kind of incredible to watch this. I'm so
thrilled to hear you had a a little
piece of this, Alex. The for me this was
incredibly exciting because, you know,
it gives us a way of manipulating our
neurons and and some people freak out
and go, "Oh my god, you're kind of
playing with the brain." And my
responses, we have an old word for this.
We call it marketing. Uh use different
techniques to try and create a response
in the brain. When somebody sees a Coke,
you want them to get thirsty. All we're
doing is exponentially accelerating it
with technology and the ability to turn
off and on neural circus gives you this
magical readr capability which we've
always wanted for the brain. So this is
super exciting.
>> Nice
your thoughts.
>> Yeah, I think you know it does take
years and years for Nobel prizes but
really Nobel prizes apart from economics
which is a bit of a weird one. We can
put that to the side. um dismal science
and all uh they have to be for applied
science now right like anything
theoretical you know when you had
Georgie glassau when you've had kind of
even alpha fold and other things like
the Nobel committee can't keep up with
and how much of it is now AI versus
human on the purely theoretical side so
I think you should be the Nobel Prize
for applied sciences shall we say but we
should really reward and maybe come up
with another prize for some of the crazy
breakthroughs and other things that
humans and AIS together will be able to
do and I think again there'll be massive
theoretical advances, new science and
kind of other things that should be
awarded and especially should be awarded
to everyone not just the PI. Um but you
know this again is a fantastic result
and we're seeing continued things around
this on photonics and kind of more and
yeah I think it's a solid prize but
again Nobel itself applied sciences I
think is the way
>> the Nobel Prize might just become super
quaint. It'd be like that Plymouth Rock
village where they go and churn butter
because you like basically 20 years from
now they'll be saying we're giving this
Nobel Prize. Remember way back before AI
when you had to actually think through
this stuff manually. This this team here
did this thing. We're recognizing it 20
years after the fact and you know five
people will show up and go
>> well they have 20 years more of prizes
to give. You know just again pick it up
from the prei age.
>> Oh my god. I mean it's hard to believe
that all the Nobel prizes in the future
aren't going to be AI derived.
>> It's going to be we've started to see it
already. Demis with Alphafold and Jeff
Hinton with the RBM which [snorts] I
mean parenthetically I don't know anyone
who uses Boltzman machines so that that
one's a bit of a question mark but yeah
I think we we've already we've started
to see AI prizes in physics and
chemistry already. I expect to see many
many more.
>> Wait that Bman one is really important.
So Jeffrey Hinton absolutely deserved
the Nobel Prize for back prop 100%. But
it's not physics. It's not eligible. But
you're right. So they they're like,
"What else did he do?" Okay, here's a
boltsmith. Nobody uses this thing.
>> That was a weird one. No one uses. Come
on.
>> Yeah. They wanted to give a Nobel Prize
for AI. That's what [laughter]
>> we need [snorts] one in economics now
for AI. That's what
>> cost. Totally. Byson, man.
>> Yeah. So this morning the Nobel Prize
committee gave one out in physics to
Francis Halen uh University of Wisconsin
Madison for decisive contributions to
the ice cube nutrino observatory and the
discovery of high energy nutrinos of
astrophysical origin. Alex, do you want
to explain this one? Yeah, this is again
sort of an artifact of the way some of
these prizes are awarded where in effect
they have to be awarded to a person but
really if if you look at how Ice Cube is
organized or how CERN is organized these
are massive organizations with lots of
people and what typically happens is as
a way of rewarding the organization and
the effort itself it's awarded to the
lead for the organization. Ice Cube has
played a seinal role in enabling us to
observe cosmic nutrinos and high energy
nutrinos in general. There's a such a
beautiful history there. I remember one
of the most startling nutrino results
that I had seen over the past several
decades was uh seeing a ring of nutrinos
in again one of these similar
observatories usually underground
usually filled with heavy water. a ring
of nutrinos or flashes arising from
ultimately uh nutrinos colliding with
nuclei. Nutrinos obviously have a
vanishingly small cross-section uh of
interaction with uh with the nuclei of
atoms. Seeing a ring a circle that was
the result of a supernova and nutrinos
one of the one of the most interesting
areas of the standard model for sure. uh
there still isn't a textbook established
rest mass for nutrinos. Physicists are
still trying to box in what the rest
masses of the the the three known
species uh of uh of electron or of
nutrinos even are. And and so yeah, I I
think this is an interesting prize. If
if I were to armchair quarterback this
one, I'd say this is a prize being
awarded to a very large uh very uh
ownorous, shall we say, consortium to to
observe nutrinos. I think the challenge
with physics more broadly, and maybe
this ties in with the Jeff Hinton
comment, is there has been a maybe get
in trouble for this, but don't care.
there there has been a noticeable
deficit of fundamental physics advances
in the past 50ish years. And so if if
you're trying to decide which Nobel
prizes to award, you know, to emod to
your earlier comments about
applications, if if there is a a
striking deficit of a half century in
fundamental physics, then you're stuck
awarding it to applications. I for one,
you know, one of the reasons why I
co-founded physical super intelligence.
I'll talk my book for a few seconds is
to try to revive advances in all of
physics, not just the applications of
physics because we've gone arguably
about a half century plus without
fundamental advances. So we're trying to
bring about a second physics golden age
for what it's worth.
>> Yeah. Just for fun uh to explain Ice
Cube. So the ice cube nutrino
observatory fills a cubic kilometer of
ice with light sensors, right? that's
looking for nutrino flashes as as Alex
said when the nutrino hits the atomic
nucleus. And just a fun fact, every
second you have 65 billion nutrinos that
pass through you from the sun without
you ever noticing. So yeah, these
detectors are are definitely an unusual
sort.
65 billion. See, did you notice?
>> I did not know that. And I'm not sure I
needed to know that feel.
>> They're they're interesting. Like what
when so I spent some time at Bell Labs
doing dark matter research and we used
to talk at Royal Wii the the staff used
to talk about what could we do with
nutrinos. So like a nutrino phone for
example would have tremendous
applications you could imagine and firm
lab a number of years back made
[clears throat] a bit of progress in
this direction. Right now, if you want
to communicate between two opposite
sides of the Earth, you're stuck at best
using low Earth orbit satellites, which
give you refractive index of of one sort
of speed of light transmission, but you
don't have line of sight. If if you want
to do say pear trading between New York
and London, you're stuck going around
geodessics on the Earth's surface with
either LEO constellations or holo core
fiber and nutrinos. In principle, if we
could rig up a nutrino phone, we could
just shoot nutrinos directly through the
Earth and have ultra- low latency
communication between two different
parts of Earth without needing to go
around the Earth's surface. So, if the
audience needs to be motivated to care
about progress in nutrinos, imagine
being able to just send information
directly through the Earth among many
other applications. So, if you're
Starlink, you just need a cubic
kilometer of ice to catch it. [laughter]
>> Yeah. Per per handset. All right, let's
go to the AMAs. Um, uh, Alex, this first
one's for you.
>> Yeah. Okay. So, AI personhood again.
AWG, what's your timeline for AI
personhood? And this is from Joshua
Barios 9452.
So, different timelines in different
places. I think in Argentina, we're
essentially there for some variant of AI
corporate personhood, whereas in say the
US, I think it's going to take longer
and I think it's going to be more
incremental. I think we'll start to see
various forms of economic AI personhood
like enabling AI agents to open their
bank their own bank accounts
autonomously. Now to soon social social
personhood where AI agents can open
their own say social media accounts
fully autonomously without needing to be
tied back to a human supervisor sometime
soon. I I think in in America in the
west there's probably a strong antipathy
towards say enabling AI persons to vote
in human elections that's probably last
to never I would hypothesize but I I
think broadly in the US at least I I
think 5 to 10year incremental roadmap
for rolling out individual say rights
very granular rights not it won't be an
all or nothing proposition but
granularly rolling these is out over the
next few years. Other parts of the world
maybe never. Uh Argentina now it's going
to be a spectrum.
>> Interesting. See, your choice.
>> Let me go with uh number four. Um once
we had recursive self-improvement, is it
then just a matter of how much compute
is available? And that's from Chris
Dover 8507.
I think it's not quite that simple.
Compute obviously matters but
intelligence improvement has lots of
different components to it like we
talked about the shortage in RAM
already. You have energy as a substrate.
Uh you want to evaluate whether a change
uh like actually improve the system or
not. So there'll be some peripheral
components of recursive sub improvement
that will slow the overall progress
down. So it just doesn't it doesn't mean
you have an instant intelligence
explosion. The implementation of that
will take time. However, once you have
AI systems that can improve the the
research cycle, uh you get a massive
compression of the innovation cycle and
that's what we're seeing with the time
scale going from years between models
down to 10 11 days and that's the
mechanism for the singularity. So the we
think of the I would think of the
singularity not as infinite like
intelligence but it's when the iteration
cycle gets so fast that we can't no
longer keep up which is why we're in the
middle of it now. There's no model by
which you can predict the future today
and that is the very definition of a
singularity. You can't see past that
event horizon.
>> Uh Dave, your choice.
>> You get stuck with two if I take three.
Sorry. All right. I'm taking three. Why
can't a majority of the compute
resources go towards solving the
community issues with data centers now
so people will believe AI can solve
problems that matter to voters? Um, you
know, I actually have a very related
question I think about a lot, which is
the the PR around the AI labs is so bad
because they didn't really manage it and
it grew much faster than they thought it
would. But now they've got this power
tool of AI that's insanely convincing
and brilliant at coming up with
messaging. So I think they can convince
the people around the data centers that
they're getting a huge benefit using AI
as a as a tool in that process. I also
think they can give like the cost of
benefiting the town is so small
>> compared to the value of the data
center.
>> I'm like why don't they wake up and just
say we're going to give you far better
you know uh cost of electricity and
schools and police ports. We're going to
subsidize everything here. It's a
fraction of the revenue they're going to
make.
>> This is one of those many topics where
if you take what Peter just said and you
walk into their office and you say, "I
know exactly how to solve this problem
in Abalene in whatever." I I'm going to
work night and day, they'll just start
paying you tomorrow because the only
reason they're not on it is because
they're stretched way too thin.
>> And somebody just needs to take their
money and fill the void.
>> And because you know, nobody knows like
in Abalene, what do we need? Better
schools? Do we need better busing? I
don't know. Oh, and just like I just
arrived like, okay, somebody come and
fill that space and I swear to God
they'll hire you tomorrow and they'll
pay you whatever it takes.
>> Emod, mosquitoes, can they be helpful
inoculators?
>> Tweak their genes so they deliver
measles vaccines instead of disease.
That's Thomas Davis real estate. Uh, I
don't think we should have forced
vaccination for large numbers of people.
And I'm actually on the genocidal
mosquitoes uh side of things. They've
killed 5 billion people over history, a
million total. And so I wouldn't mind if
they were actually just wiped out. But
definitely don't force vaccination. And
I think actually we should like remove
the mosquitoes. They are the biggest
predator for humans.
>> But the concept is interesting, right?
To use this, you know, automated uh
living drone capability to distribute
something that's helpful and useful. But
I agree with you.
>> Psilocybin
psilocybin mosquitoes.
>> We went there. I just how about just
vaccinating the mosquitoes? I mean,
mosquitoes have a problem, too.
Mosquitoes are [laughter]
>> Yeah, just tiny little syringe.
>> But I'm I'm curious. I mean, there
there's a more general problem here,
which is we live in a biosphere that's
nature red in tooth and claw. It's
filled with wild animal suffering. My
view on wild animal suffering is that
it's an atrocity that we should see if
we can fix. But I I assume Immad based
on your comments, your attitude is no,
just eradicate all mosquitoes
everywhere.
>> Well, Ben Lamb could bring him back
anyway. Let's
>> Jean,
>> but he refuses to. I pressed Ben on
that. And Ben's attitude is no, we're
going to only, you know, laser focus on
a few things. Don't ask me about Mozart.
>> Oh, yeah. The tiny little woolly mammoth
and the pterodactylsized mosquito.
That's what we're
>> Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. You want the
pterodactylized [laughter] mosquito. No,
let's please not.
>> Just go Just go to Northern Canada. They
have pterodactyl size. All right, Iman,
you get first choice now.
>> All right. Um,
boo. Uh, do you think some politicians
resist AI because it could fundamentally
change how politics works? Uh, at Daniel
Morris one. Yes, of course. I mean, like
it will remove a lot of the barriers for
democracy, intelligence access, raise
the intelligence of society. Like these
are big things. So I think you will get
some resistance to that as we see this
kind of evolve because many politicians
unfortunately don't want a more
intelligent electorate particularly the
ones that focus on uh shall we say more
demagoguic approaches.
>> Okay. Uh Salem
>> uh I got to take number five here. What
happens when intelligence rises uh rises
while cost collapses from BB_X_1
uh like you know when you have
intelligence going from a scarce
commodity or scarce capability embedded
in very expensive clunky humans um you
basically radically change not just the
company itself but civilization itself
right because whenever the cost of some
foundational input approaches zero we
actually reorganize our whole world
around it. Now that information
transmission is essentially free, we
rewritten our entire world around that.
So when bandwidth became cheap, you got
YouTube and you got Zoom and you got
cloud computing and all that kind of
stuff. When computation became cheap, we
got cell phones and smartphones. When
intelligence becomes cheap, we redesign
companies. We do unbelievable research.
You rethink education. You rethink
healthcare. Then you have scarce things
like human experience, judgment,
purpose, uh trust, etc. that become
important. Then you you stop optimizing
intelligence, which is what we've been
doing for several thousand years, and
you start optimizing what do you point
it at? That becomes interesting.
>> Yeah. I I think again I'm going to make
the point here. We've said it so many
times as this happens, it's so
incredibly important for people to raise
the limit on what they think they can
do, you know, and and point that
intelligence at something extraordinary
that surprises you because you're going
to be able to make massive contributions
by utilizing it. All right, Dave.
>> Uh why don't I take seven? Richard, I
think that's Richard Socher, puts P Doom
at zero yet says 100 million people
could be harmed. I think that did he say
that on our podcast?
>> I [snorts] don't remember that.
>> Maybe.
>> He definitely got a lot of he he was
open and super honest. You should
definitely watch that podcast. Uh so
question, should P doom mean extinction
or catastrophe? And how should we think
about risks of that scale? And that's
from a really long name, 6542.
Um
yeah I I think uh everything in that
question is exactly right. Um we can
define pdoom I think it's doom like doom
is doom. P doom should be probability of
of extinction disaster catastrophe.
That's sort of what it means. But yeah
there's there's inevitably going to be
misuse of AI uh and it's going to cause
harm. And as Eric Schmidt has said on
the podcast at least three times, uh
he's hoping it's relatively small, like
a 100 people, a thousand people are
affected or it's a cyber attack that
nobody's hurt but money is taken and
that's what wakes up the governments.
But right now, they're just not moving
anywhere near fast enough to avert it.
Yet, the good outweighs the bad by
incredible amounts. And I think that was
Richard's uh fundamental point that we
should expect abundance and overall
benefit. So, I don't know if we should
redefine P Doom, but uh but that's the
way it's going to play out.
>> Uh and we should just keep on focusing
on Pab. All right, Alex, number six is
for you. All right, number six. Could
public opinion become a greater
bottleneck than the technological
development of RSI, recursive
self-improvement itself? And this is
from David K, VFX. I think we're already
there. I I think recursive
self-improvement, we're already in the
RSI era. both anthropic and open AAI
have made a number of pretty detailed
and quantitative public statements to
that effect. So we're already in an era
when RSI is driving the vast majority of
research at this point. Whereas on the
other side of the ledger, public opinion
is driving data centers out of at least
American municipalities in the direction
of orbit on the one hand and we see as
discussed in the the past pod with
Richard, we see members of the US House
introducing or planning to introduce
bills against recursive
self-improvement. I think public opinion
probably is already a greater bottleneck
than the actual intrinsic technical
difficulty of RSI, which is also why you
see some of the public labs, uh, some of
the frontier labs rather, like Anthropic
starting to make public noises about
essentially buying off public opinion by
doing, you know, tiny little things like
solving all human disease. And if if you
can c solve all human disease as a side
effect of recursive self-improvement,
then maybe public will look the other
way. Not that it's a bad thing, but at
least be uh, you know, compensated in
some sense for allowing many of the
tokens, maybe the vast majority of the
tokens to flow to self-improvement
rather than to other applications. I
think there's probably a pretty good
bargain, a grand bargain if you will, to
be struck there.
>> Nice. A reminder, if you've got an outro
video and Dave, I expect you to submit
some here. Uh, please send it to media
dmmadis.com.
And we've got a beautiful one from our
friend uh friend of the pod CJ Truhart.
>> I have a quick announcement.
>> Um, we've been doing these workshops for
teenagers. Lily is going to run one in
Austin, Texas on the 24th. If anybody
has teenagers or wants them to kind of
rethink how to use AI as a superpower,
um, check it out. Yxo.orld world. We'll
put a link in the
>> yxo.world.world.
>> Nice.
>> Um, and they've got slots for a few
teenagers left for anybody interested.
>> All right. If you're in Austin, bring
your teen. Uh, Lily does an amazing job.
All right. This this video is called
Tomorrow Comes Alive. It is from the
Moonshots Live event. Take a look.
>> CJ is awesome.
6:00 a.m.
A new day,
a new world waiting.
6 a.m. The alarm breaks the silence.
[music] Close on the chair, blue light
in the room. Let the eyes of the man in
the mirror said, "Remember what you came
here to do." Through hotel doors into a
ride share day break running over the
glass carrying a future I
[music and singing] could almost see but
no one brings the future back alone.
>> Can you hear it?
>> That quiet calling getting loud. [music]
>> Comes a fire in a crowd.
[music]
If you got a purpose burning brighter
than your fear. [music]
If you see a world worth building that
has never yet been here, don't wait for
tomorrow
become what you believe. Star Trek made
tomorrow [music]
something we could see. Moon shots make
tomorrow [singing]
something we can be.
>> Come alive, come alive. Dreaming beauty,
[music] bring it to life. And moon shots
live.
Tomorrow comes alive.
Tomorrow comes alive. [music]
>> Walked into a wave of voices. [music]
>> Strangers felt like future friends.
>> Every [singing] handshake [music] held a
story.
>> Every question crossed the edge.
>> Not abundance as a [music] slogan. I
just talk about the climb. Courage
recognizing courage. Vision multiplied
by mine. Someone met me at the doorway.
Not with a pitch but with a hug. Before
[music] we ever spoke of rockets made
the future feel like us in the dream
grew hands and heartbeat. When the room
became a crew and the distance felt much
[music] closer when I saw what we could
do. Can you feel it?
>> The whole room breathing out.
>> A thousand different sparks
>> make a constellation in the crowd.
[music]
If you got a purpose burning brighter
than your fear. [music]
IF YOU SEE A WORLD WORTH building that
has never yet been here, don't wait for
tomorrow [music]
become what you believe. Star Trek made
tomorrow
something we could see. [music]
Moonshots makes tomorrow
something we can be.
>> Come alive. Come alive.
>> Dreaming beauty bring it to life. And
tomorrow
>> I love that. A purpose burning brighter
than your fear. What a great line.
>> That uh character is C the guy walking.
>> CJ wrote himself into the video.
>> Yeah, that was really [laughter] good.
>> Yeah, that was awesome.
>> My brain is so fried, guys. I mean, what
the hell?
>> I [laughter] know.
>> Singularities are exhausting, aren't
they, Sim?
>> Jesus Christ.
>> I'm glad this only happens once once a
planet
>> at Well, maybe like maybe it happens
more than once per planet. We don't know
yet.
>> Yeah. Ah, well, I'm on stage for 5 days
at the abundance longevity trip here.
>> We got 40 amazing faculty on the cutting
edge of longevity. Yeah, longevity
escape velocity. It's coming fast.
>> We're going to need longevity just to
live through these episodes,
>> dude.
No idea. [laughter]
Uh, Immod, Alex, See, Dave, love you
guys.